<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Normal distribution">

<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal1" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal1" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal1">The normal distribution's pdf is given and the standard normal distribution is defined.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal2" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal2" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal2">The mean and variance of the standard normal distribution are derived and used to find the mean and variance of other normal distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal3" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal3" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal3">All normal distributions have the same shape when expressed in terms of standard deviations from the mean; these are called z-scores and have standard normal distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal4" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal4" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal4">Excel can be used to find probabilities about normal distributions. Translating questions into ones about z-scores gives a method to find probabilities using tables of probabilities for the standard normal distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal5" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal5" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal5">We usually want to find a cumulative probability corresponding to a given x-value. Occasionally the x-value corresponding to a given cumulative probability is needed — a quantile of the distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal6" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal6" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal6">A linear combination of two independent normal variables also has a normal distribution. So do the mean and sum of the values in a random sample.</page>
<page dir="en/normal" filePrefix="normal7" summaryDir="en/normal" summaryFilePrefix="s_normal7" videoDir="en/normal" videoFilePrefix="v_normal7">The mean and variance of a random sample from a normal distribution are independent.</page>
</section>
