<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Estimating parameters">

<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst1" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst1" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst1">Bias, standard error, mean squared error and consistency are defined in the same way for estimators of parameters in discrete and continuous distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst2" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst2" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst2">If a distribution has a single unknown parameter, its method of moments estimator is the value that makes the distribution's mean equal to the mean of a random sample. The method of moments estimator for the maximum of a rectangular distribution is found.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst3" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst3" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst3">The likelihood function of a continuous distribution's parameter is the product of the probability density functions of a random sample. The maximum likelihood estimate is usually found by setting the derivative of the log-likelihood to zero.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst4" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst4" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst4">Maximum likelihood estimators are asymptotically unbiased with normal distributions. A formula is given for the approximate standard error.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst5" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst5" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst5">An approximate 95% confidence interval is the maximum likelihood estimate ± 1.96 standard errors. Replacing &amp;quot;1.96&amp;quot; with other constants gives other confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst6" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst6" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst6">The maximum likelihood estimate of a normal distribution's mean is found. The asymptotic formula for the standard error of the estimator gives the exact standard error.</page>
<page dir="en/continuousEst" filePrefix="continuousEst7" summaryDir="en/continuousEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_continuousEst7" videoDir="en/continuousEst" videoFilePrefix="v_continuousEst7">The maximum likelihood estimate of the maximum of a rectangular distribution is at a discontinuity of the likelihood function and cannot be found by differentiating the log-likelihood.</page>
</section>
