<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Describing centre and spread">


<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread1" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread1">The centre of a distribution is a 'typical value'. The spread describes how far the values are from the centre.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread2" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread2">The median is a summary of the centre of a distribution. The range and inter-quartile range both describe spread.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread3" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread3">The median and mean are alternative measures of the centre of a distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread4" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread4">When a data set is not symmetric, the mean and median may differ substantially.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread5" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread5">The standard deviation is the most commonly used numerical summary of the spread of values in a data set.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread6" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread6">The 70-95-100 rule-of-thumb is useful for understanding the numerical value of the standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread7" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread7">It is possible to roughly guess the mean and standard deviation from a histogram and roughly sketch a symmetric histogram matching any given mean and standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread8" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread8">The mean and standard deviation cannot give any indication of the existance of outliers, skewness or clusters. A dot plot or histogram should be examined before reporting these numerical summaries.</page>
<page dir="en/counts" filePrefix="counts4" nameOverride="Mean and st devn for discrete data" summaryDir="en/counts" summaryFilePrefix="s_counts4">The mean and standard deviation can be evaluated easily from a frequency table.</page>

</section>
