<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Histograms and density">
<topText><![CDATA[
	<p>A histogram does not separately display the individual values. In large data sets it displays the major features of the distribution  better than dot plots or stem and leaf plots.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density1" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density1">The heights of the stacks of crosses in a dot plot describe the density of values.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density2" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density2">In a simple histogram, the height of the rectangle above each class on the axis equals the number of values in the class -- the class frequency.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density3" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density3">Class width and start-point should be chosen to make the histogram as smooth as possible -- neither too blocky nor too jagged.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density4" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density4">The shape of a histogram can be very dependent on the choice of classes if the data set is small; beware over-interpreting its shape. Stacked dot plots are a better display of small data sets.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density5" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density5">In a histogram, the proportion of the total area that is above any class equals the relative frequency of the class.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density6" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density6">The vertical axis should be relative frequency, not frequency, when comparing two groups with histograms. Population pyramids are often used to compare age distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density7" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density7">If a histogram has varying class widths, the vertical axis must be 'density'. The histogram shape would be misleading if frequency or relative frequency was used for the vertical axis.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density8" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density8">The proportion of values in any classes always equals the proportion of the total histogram area that is above the classes.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density9" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density9">Frequency polygons are closely related to histograms but give a less 'blocky' display of density. Different groups can be compared more easily with them.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density10" note="(optional)" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density10">Kernel density estimates show density in a still smoother display.</page>

</section>
