<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic SYSTEM "exerciseXmlDefn.dtd">

<topic name='ciMean'>
<longName>Confidence intervals for mean</longName>


<exercise name='ciFromMeanSe'>
	<description>Find 2se approx 95% CI for a range of parameters</description>
	<comment>An estimate and standard error are given in some context and they must be used to find an approximate 95% CI based on (estimate +/- 2 standard errors). Variations use several different parameter types.</comment>
	<applet>exerciseEstimProg.GenericCiApplet</applet>
	<width>500</width>
	<height>450</height>
	
	<variable name="intervalWording" type="int_choice(Find a 95% CI#We are 95% confident of between...)">Alternative formats for question and answer layout</variable>
	<variable name="estimate" type="double">Value of parameter estimate</variable>
	<variable name="se" type="double">Standard error of parameter</variable>
	
	<template>
		<question>A parameter estimate is #estimate(20.00:30.00)# with standard error #se(0.40:0.70)#. #?:string[intervalWording](Find a 95% confidence interval for the parameter.*We are about 95% confident that the parameter is...)# </question>
		<qnParam>intervalWording(0:1)</qnParam>
	</template>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>bmi</shortName>
		<longName>Mean body mass index</longName>
		<question>A person's body mass index (BMI) is defined to be body weight (in kg) divided by height (in metres) squared and is a commonly used indicator of obesity. As part of a study of regional variations in obesity, BMI was found from a random sample of n=#?:int(40:80)# adult men in a region.\\nThe mean body mass index (BMI) in the sample was #estimate(20.00:30.00)# with standard error #se(0.40:0.70)#. #?:string[intervalWording](Find a 95% confidence interval for the mean BMI of adult men in the region.*We are about 95% confident that the mean BMI of adult men in the region will be...)#</question>
		<qnParam>intervalWording(0:1)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>cancerRisk</shortName>
		<longName>Effect of cigars on cancer risk</longName>
		<question>A study of the health risks of smoking cigars estimated that the probability of dying from a particular type of cancer in the ten years of the study was #estimate(3.0:7.0)#% higher for cigar smokers than for non-smokers with a standard error of #se(1.0:3.0)#%.\\n#?:string[intervalWording](Find a 95% confidence interval for the extra risk of dying from this type of cancer in ten years that is due to cigar smoking.*We are about 95% confident that the extra risk of dying from this type of cancer in ten years due to cigar smoking is...)#</question>
		<qnParam>intervalWording(0:1)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>shopClosures</shortName>
		<longName>Percentage of shops closing</longName>
		<question>From a survey of small retailers that were in business in the previous year, it was found that #estimate(4.0:10.0)#% had since shut down with a standard error of #se(1.0:2.0)#%.\\n#?:string[intervalWording](Find a 95% confidence interval for the percentage of all small retailers who have shut down in the previous year.*We are about 95% confident that the proportion of small retailers who have shut down in the previous year will be...)#</question>
		<qnParam>intervalWording(0:1)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>frictionWeld</shortName>
		<longName>Effect of velocity on strength of friction welding</longName>
		<question>Friction welding is used to join different metals that cannot be easily joined by other means -- a fast-moving component is brought into contact with a stationary one to fuse the materials at the join. In an experiment, several velocities were used for the moving component and the strength of the resulting bond was measured at each.\\nIt is estimated that the mean breaking strength of the weld increases by #estimate(5.0:10.0)# for each 1 ft/sec increase in velocity, an estimate with standard error of #se(0.3:1.0)#.\\n#?:string[intervalWording](Find a 95% confidence interval for the mean increase in breaking strength if velocity is increased by 1 ft/sec.*We are about 95% confident that increasing velocity by 1 ft/sec will increase the mean breaking strength by...)#</question>
		<qnParam>intervalWording(0:1)</qnParam>
	</variation>
</exercise>


<exercise name='findCiForMean'>
	<description>Find confidence interval for a mean</description>
	<comment>Given a sample mean and sample standard deviation, find a confidence interval for the underlying population mean. Variations can provide the population standard deviation.</comment>
	<applet>exerciseEstimProg.CiMeanApplet</applet>
	<width>550</width>
	<height>630</height>
	
	<option name="onlyNormal">Template for looking up quantiles is for normal distribution (default shows t or normal). Only select this option if all variations have known sigma.</option>
	<option name="only95">Restrict the confidence level to 95% (default is randomly 90, 95 or 99%)</option>
	
	<variable name="varName" type="string"></variable>
	<variable name="units" type="string"></variable>
	<variable name="axis" type="axis"></variable>
	<variable name="popnSd" type="double(optional)"></variable>
	<variable name="mean" type="double"></variable>
	<variable name="sd" type="double"></variable>
	<variable name="maxPlusMinus" type="double"></variable>
	<variable name="noOfValues" type="int(1)"></variable>
	<variable name="ciLevel" type="random"></variable>
	
	<template>
		<question>A type of measurement has standard deviation #sigma#=#popnSd(0.0068)# cm. The stacked dot plot describes a sample of n=#noOfValues(3:12)# values.Find a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the mean, µ.</question>
		<qnParam>varName(Variable, Y)#units(cm)#axis(0.72 0.76 0.72 0.01)#mean(0.742)#sd(0.0068)#maxPlusMinus(9.9999)</qnParam>
	</template>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>activeIngredient</shortName>
		<longName>Active ingredient in drug (known sigma)</longName>
		<height>700</height>
		<question>A pharmaceutical company routinely tests products to check that the concentration of an active ingredient is within tight limits. The results from one type of analysis vary around the true concentration with standard deviation #sigma#=#popnSd[index](0.0068,0.0068,0.068,0.068)# grams per litre. The stacked dot plot below shows the results of n=#noOfValues(3:12)# repeated analyses of the same product.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the true concentration of active ingredient in this product.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:3)#varName(Concentration, gm/litre)#units(gm/litre)#axis[index](0.72 0.76 0.72 0.01*0.40 0.44 0.40 0.01*7.2 7.6 7.2 0.1*5.2 5.6 5.2 0.1)#mean[index](0.742,0.422,7.42,5.42)#sd[index](0.0068,0.0068,0.068,0.068)#maxPlusMinus[index](9.9999,9.9999,9.999,9.999)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>activeIngredient2</shortName>
		<longName>Active ingredient in drug (unknown sigma)</longName>
		<height>700</height>
		<question>A pharmaceutical company routinely tests products to check that the concentration of an active ingredient is within tight limits. A new method of analysis is being tried and, although it is known that the results vary between repeat analyses of the same product, the population standard deviation, #sigma#, is unknown. The stacked dot plot below shows the results of n=#noOfValues(3:12)# repeated analyses of the same product.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the true concentration of active ingredient in this product.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:3)#varName(Concentration, gm/litre)#units(gm/litre)#axis[index](0.72 0.76 0.72 0.01*0.40 0.44 0.40 0.01*7.2 7.6 7.2 0.1*5.2 5.6 5.2 0.1)#mean[index](0.742,0.422,7.42,5.42)#sd[index](0.0068,0.0068,0.068,0.068)#maxPlusMinus[index](9.9999,9.9999,9.999,9.999)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>plantSugar</shortName>
		<longName>Soluble sugar in plants (known sigma)</longName>
		<height>700</height>
		<question>A laboratory procedure for assessing soluble sugar in plants is such that in the range 100 to 200 milligrams (mg) of glucose per gram of dry weight, repeat measurements vary around the true glucose concentration with standard deviation #sigma#=#popnSd(3.1)# mg/gram dry weight. The stacked dot plot below shows the results of n=#noOfValues(3:12)# repeated analyses of the same plant.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the true glucose concentration in this plant.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:1)#varName(Glucose concentration)#units(mg/gm dry weight)#axis[index](133 147 134 2*155 169 156 2)#mean[index](140,162)#sd(3.10)#maxPlusMinus(999.99)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>plantSugar2</shortName>
		<longName>Soluble sugar in plants (unknown sigma)</longName>
		<height>700</height>
		<question>A laboratory procedure is used to assess soluble sugar in plants but although repeat measurements vary around the true glucose concentration the population standard deviation, #sigma#, is unknown. The stacked dot plot below shows the results of n=#noOfValues(3:12)# repeated analyses of the same plant.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the true glucose concentration in this plant.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:1)#varName(Glucose concentration)#units(mg/gm dry weight)#axis[index](133 147 134 2*155 169 156 2)#mean[index](140,162)#sd(3.10)#maxPlusMinus(999.99)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>appleWeight</shortName>
		<longName>Weights of apples (uknown sigma)</longName>
		<question>The stacked dot plot below shows the weights of n=#noOfValues(20:40)# apples sampled by a supermarket from a large batch that was delivered by a supplier.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the mean weight of apples from this supplier.</question>
		<qnParam>varName(Weight, grams)#units(grams)#axis(100 130 100 5)#mean(110:120)#sd(5.00)#maxPlusMinus(999.99)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>patientHeight</shortName>
		<longName>Heights of patients with disease (uknown sigma)</longName>
		<question>A researcher measured the heights of n=#noOfValues(5:30)# adult female patients who suffered from a particular disease. The stacked dot plot below summarises their heights.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the mean height of patients with this disease.</question>
		<qnParam>varName(Height, cm)#units(cm)#axis(150 200 150 10)#mean(170:180)#sd(10.00)#maxPlusMinus(999.99)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>callTime</shortName>
		<longName>Duration of bank phone calls (uknown sigma)</longName>
		<height>660</height>
		<question>The call centre for a bank samples n=#noOfValues(10:40)# incoming phone calls and records the time taken to answer each. The call times for one day are shown in the diagram below and are used to estimate the mean call duration for that day.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the mean call time of all such calls.</question>
		<qnParam>varName(Call time, sec)#units(seconds)#axis(0 200 0 50)#mean(80:120)#sd(30.0)#maxPlusMinus(999.9)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>calories</shortName>
		<longName>Calorie intake in African town (uknown sigma)</longName>
		<question>The calorie intake was recorded from a random sample of n=#noOfValues(5:15)# adults in an African town.\\nFind a #ciLevel(:)#% confidence interval for the mean calorie intake per person in towns of this kind.</question>
		<qnParam>varName(Calorie intake)#units(calories)#axis(1800 2800 1800 200)#mean(2150:2450)#sd(170)#maxPlusMinus(9999)</qnParam>
	</variation>
</exercise>


<exercise name='factorsAffectingCiWidth'>
	<description>Complete statements about how n, s and the conf level affect CI</description>
	<comment>Three statements are presented about the effect of the sample size, sample standard deviation and confidence level on the width of a CI for the mean. Pop-up menus can be used to correct any wrong statements.</comment>
	<applet>exerciseEstimProg.CiWidthInfluencesApplet</applet>
	<width>600</width>
	<height>650</height>
	
	<coreParam name="noOfStatements">3</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="statementStart0">A #?:string[ciLevel](90*95*95*99)#% confidence interval for the mean has been calculated from a random sample of n=#?:int[](20,30,40,50)# values. If the confidence level is changed from #?:string[ciLevel](90% to 95%*95% to 99%*95% to 90%*99% to 95%)#, the width of the confidence interval will ...</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="messages0">If we make our confidence interval #?:string[ciLevel](wider*wider*narrower*narrower)#, it contains #?:string[ciLevel](more*more*fewer*fewer)# values so there is #?:string[ciLevel](more*more*less*less)# chance that it will include the population parameter. We must therefore #?:string[ciLevel](increase*increase*decrease*decrease)# the width of the confidence interval to get a #?:string[ciLevel](higher*higher*lower*lower)# confidence level.</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="statementStart1">A #?:string[](90%*95%*99%)# confidence interval for the mean has been found from a random sample of n=#?:string[sampleSize](10*20*20*30)# values. If the sample size had been n=#?:string[sampleSize](20*30*10*20)# instead, we would have expected the confidence interval to have been ...</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="messages1">#?:string[sampleSize](More*More*Less*Less)# data implies #?:string[sampleSize](more*more*less*less)# information about the population parameter so we should be able to estimate it #?:string[sampleSize](more*more*less*less)# accurately. We would therefore expect #?:string[sampleSize](a decrease*a decrease*an increase*an increase)# in the width of the confidence interval.</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="statementStart2">Random samples of n=#?:int[](20,30,40,50)# values are selected from each of two populations. If the standard deviation in population A is #?:string[spread](greater*larger*less*smaller)# than that in population B, we would expect the #?:string[](90%*95%*99%)# confidence interval for the mean of population A to be ...</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="statementEnd2">that from population B.</coreParam>
	<coreParam name="messages2">If the values in population #?:string[spread](A*A*B*B)# are more variable than those in population #?:string[spread](B*B*A*A)#, population #?:string[spread](A*A*B*B)#'s mean will also be more variable and will be a less accurate estimate of the population mean. The confidence interval from population #?:string[spread](A*A*B*B)# would therefore be expected to be wider.</coreParam>
	
	<variable name="ciLevel" type="int_choice(increased width -- 90 to 95#increased width -- 95 to 99#decreased width -- 95 to 90#decreased width -- 99 to 95)">CI width change for the four possible changes in CI level</variable>
	<variable name="sampleSize" type="int_choice(narrower -- n=10 to 20#narrower -- n=20 to 30#wider -- n=20 to 10#wider -- n=30 to 20)">CI width change for the four possible changes to sample size</variable>
	<variable name="spread" type="int_choice(wider -- bigger sd#wider -- larger sd#narrower -- less sd#narrower -- smaller sd)"></variable>
	<variable name="menuLevel" type="string_array">Wording of the three menu options for the change in confidence level</variable>
	<variable name="menuSampleSize" type="string_array">Wording of the three menu options for the change in sample size</variable>
	<variable name="menuSpread" type="string_array">Wording of the three menu options for the change in spead of the values</variable>
	
	<!-- no template for this question  -->
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>generic</shortName>
		<longName>Generic</longName>
		<question>How is the width of a confidence interval affected by the sample size, confidence level and spread of sample values?\\nUse the pop-up menus to complete the following three statements.</question>
		<qnParam>ciLevel(0:3)#sampleSize(0:3)#spread(0:3)#menuLevel(remain_the_same increase decrease)#menuSampleSize(approximately_the_same_width narrower wider)#menuSpread(approximately_the_same_width_as wider_than narrower_than)</qnParam>
	</variation>
</exercise>


<exercise name='interpretCi'>
	<description>Pick which of 4 statements correctly interprets a 95% CI for the mean</description>
	<comment>This is a multiple choice question in which the correct statement describing a 95% confidence interval must be picked.</comment>
	<applet>exerciseEstimProg.CiInterpApplet</applet>
	<width>500</width>
	<height>550</height>
	
	<variable name="lowLimit" type="double">Lower limit of CI</variable>
	<variable name="highLimit" type="double">Upper limit of CI</variable>
	<variable name="units" type="string(10)">Units for values</variable>
	<variable name="sampleValues" type="string(40)">Text desribing sample value</variable>
	<variable name="popnValues" type="string(40)">Text desribing population values</variable>
	<variable name="newSample" type="string(40)">Text describing a further similar sample of values</variable>
	<variable name="newValue" type="string(40)">Text describing a new value sampled from the population</variable>
	<variable name="sampleStat" type="string(40)">Text describing the sample statistic</variable>
	<variable name="popnParam" type="string(40)">Text describing the population parameter</variable>
	
	<template>
		<question>A 95% confidence interval of #lowLimit(123)# to #highLimit(137)# was calculated from random sample of values.</question>
		<qnParam>sampleValues(the values in the sample)#popnValues(the values of this type in general)#newValue(a new value of this type)#newSample(a similar sample of values)#sampleStat(the mean weight of this sample)#popnParam(the population mean)</qnParam>
	</template>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>tomatoWeight</shortName>
		<longName>Weights of tomatoes</longName>
		<question>A plant breeder records the weights of a random sample of n=#?:int[](30,40,50,60)# tomatoes of a particular variety and finds that a 95% confidence interval for the mean weight is from #lowLimit[index](123,146)# to #highLimit[index](137,175)# #units(grams)#.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:1)#sampleValues(the weights of tomatoes in the sample)#popnValues(the weights of tomatoes of this variety in general)#newValue(the weight of a single new tomato of this variety)#newSample(the weights of a new sample of the same number of tomatoes of this variety)#sampleStat(the mean weight of this sample of tomatoes)#popnParam(the mean weight of all tomatoes of this variety)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>paymentTime</shortName>
		<longName>Time to payment of invoices</longName>
		<question>An accountant is auditing the books of a large company and decides to sample n=100 invoices for detailed investigation. A 95% confidence interval for the mean time it took to receive payment is from #lowLimit[index](16.3,28.8,25.1)# to #highLimit[index](21.0,31.6,46.6)# #units(days)#.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:2)#sampleValues(the times to receive payment for the sampled invoices)#popnValues(the times to receive payment for all company invoices)#newValue(the time to receive payment for the next invoice)#newSample(the times to receive payment for the next 100 invoices)#sampleStat(the mean time to receive payment for this sample of invoices)#popnParam(the mean time to receive payment for all company invoices)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>rainfall</shortName>
		<longName>Annual rainfall</longName>
		<question>A climatologist records annual rainfall in a region for n=35 years. Assuming that there is no climate change and that these years give a random sample out of all rainfalls, a 95% confidence interval for the mean annual rainfall in the region is from #lowLimit[index](1005,853,1661)# to #highLimit[index](1024,971,1899)# #units(mm)#.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:2)#sampleValues(the annual rainfalls in the 35 years for which records were kept)#popnValues(the annual rainfalls in this region in general)#newValue(the annual rainfall in the next year)#newSample(the annual rainfalls in the next 35 years)#sampleStat(the mean rainfall in the 35 years from which the confidence interval was calculated)#popnParam(the mean long-term annual rainfall in this region)</qnParam>
	</variation>
	
	<variation>
		<shortName>bloodPressure</shortName>
		<longName>Increase in blood pressure after drug</longName>
		<question>In a drug trial, n=20 mice were injected with an experimental compound and the increase in their blood pressure after 2 hours was recorded. Assuming that any change in blood pressure was caused by the drug (and that the act of receiving an injection of the same volume of water has no affect on blood pressure), a 95% confidence interval for the mean change in blood pressure caused by the drug is from #lowLimit[index](5.3,-2.6,-1.9)# to #highLimit[index](7.1,8.8,13.2)# #units(mmHg)#.</question>
		<qnParam>index(0:2)#sampleValues(the blood pressure increases for the 20 mice used in the experiment)#popnValues(the increases in blood pressure experienced when this type of mouse is given the compound in general)#newValue(the increase in blood pressure when another mouse is given the same compound)#newSample(the increases in blood pressure if another 20 mice were given the same compound)#sampleStat(the mean increase in blood pressure for the 20 mice in the experiment)#popnParam(the mean increase in mouse blood pressure attributable to this compound)</qnParam>
	</variation>
</exercise>

</topic>