<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Estimating proportions">

<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn1" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn1" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn1">The methodology for describing the accuracy of a sample mean using standard errors and confidence intervals can also be used for other parameter estimates.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn2" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn2" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn2">A sample proportion estimates the corresponding population proportion, &amp;pi;. There is likely to be an error in this estimate and these errors have a distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn_c3" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn3" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c3">The estimation errors have a type of binomial distribution that is scaled to have mean zero. Its standard deviation is the standard error of the proportion.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn_c4" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn_c4" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c4">If the sample size is high enough, the error distribution is approximately normal. This page gives a few examples for which the error distribution is found.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn_c5" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn5" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c5">A 95% confidence interval for a population proportion is the sample proportion &amp;plusmn; twice its standard deviation. Its confidence level is only approximately 95% and guidelines are given for the minimum sample size.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn6" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn6" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn6">If samples are repeatedly taken, about 95% of them result in 95% confidence intervals that include the population proportion. Guidelines are given for the minimum sample size to make the confidence level close to 95%.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn_c7" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn_c7" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c7">95% confidence intervals for proportions are found and interpreted for several data sets.</page>

</section>
