<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Comparing several means">


<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup_b1" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup1">To compare the means of several groups, a model of normal distributions in all groups is used but all group standard deviations must be assumed to be the same.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup2" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup2">The sample standard deviations in the separate groups can be combined to give a pooled estimate of the common standard deviation, &amp;sigma;.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup_b3" note="(optional)" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup3">Earlier CIs and tests for equality of two group means can be improved when the group standard deviations are known to be the same. However this refinement is not recommended for general use.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup4" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup4">Both variability between group means and variability within groups must be used to assess whether the groups differ.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup5" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup5">Variability within groups and between groups are described by sums of squares.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup_b6" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup_b6">The coefficient of determination (R-squared) is the ratio of the between-groups and total sums of squares. It is the proportion of variation that can be explained by differences between the groups.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup7" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup7">The F-ratio is a test statistic that is based on the between- and within-groups sums of squares. The associated p-value tests whether all groups have the same mean.</page>
<page dir="es/multiGroup" filePrefix="multiGroup_b8" summaryDir="en/multiGroup" summaryFilePrefix="s_multiGroup_b8">The F-test is applied to a few data sets.</page>

</section>
