<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Control charts'>

<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart1'>Many business and industrial processes are continuously monitored in order to detect problems early.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart2'>A run chart plots regular measurements from a process against time. Extreme values indicate problems with the process.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart3'>For most distributions, almost all values are within 3 standard deviations of the mean. Control limits 3s on each side of the sample mean from training data can be used to indicate problems with the process.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart4'>Runs of successive values that are s or 2s from the mean can also be used to indicate problems in the process.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart5'>False alarms occasionally happen even when the process is in control. Several successive triggers give a clearer indication of problems.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart6'>Control limits are set from variation when a process is under control then applied to future observations.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart7'>Control charts are often based on regular small samples rather than individual values. If individual values have a skew distribution, the +/- 3s limits may be exceeded in 2% or more of values. Sample means are closer to normal, so a control chart for means rarely exceeds its control limits when the process is under control.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart8'>A control chart for the range of successive samples can indicate increases in process variability.</page>
<page dir='es/controlChart' filePrefix='controlChart9'>If a problem is detected in a process, brainstorming and cause-and-effect diagrams can help to determine the cause of the problem.</page>

</section>
