<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Exercises for test 3'>
<topText><![CDATA[
		<p>The following exercises give you practice with the ten questions that will be asked in the third mastery test.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir='en/popSamp' filePrefix='e_popSamp2' nameOverride='Identify parameters and estimates'>This exercise asks whether three statements describe parameters or estimates.</page>
<page dir='en/probSim' filePrefix='e_probSim1' nameOverride='Find probability about cards or dice'>This exercise asks for probabilities about a card drawn at random from a standard pack of playing cards or when two dice are rolled.</page>
<page dir='en/probSim' filePrefix='e_probSim5' nameOverride='Probability when sampling with/without replacement'>This exercise relates to pairs of numbers drawn with or without replacement from a small finite population. The question asks for a probability about either the sum or difference of the two numbers.</page>
<page dir='en/randomPropn' filePrefix='e_randomPropn1' nameOverride='Identify binomial variables'>This exercise describes four random variables and asks which have binomial distributions.</page>
<page dir='en/randomPropn' filePrefix='e_randomPropn3' nameOverride='Find binomial prob from a barchart'>In this exercise, you will use the information in the question to set the parameters of a binomial distribution then read off the probability by dragging over the bar chart of the binomial probabilities. (The computer does the calculations.)</page>
<page dir='en/randomPropn' filePrefix='e_randomPropn5' nameOverride='Find binomial prob using normal approx'>This exercise asks for probabilities relating to a binomial distribution but requires that you use a normal approximation to evaluate them.</page>
<page dir='en/probSim' filePrefix='e_probSim4' nameOverride='Find probability for non-normal pdf'>In this exercise, probabilities are obtained from the areas under a probability density function.</page>
<page dir='bk/massey130' filePrefix='e_normalDistn1' nameOverride='Guess SD from normal pdf'>This exercise shows a normal distribution and asks you to guess its standard deviation.</page>
<page dir='bk/massey130' filePrefix='e_normalDistn3' nameOverride='Find normal probability using z-score'>This exercise asks for a normal probability. It must first be translated into a question involving a z-score.</page>
<page dir='bk/massey130' filePrefix='e_normalDistn5' nameOverride='Find a normal quantile'>The exercise on this page ask the inverse question; given a probability, what is the corresponding range of values? The exercise uses a normal table to find the answer.</page>

</section>
