<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Linear model assumptions'>

<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem1'>This page gives examples where the normal linear model assumptions are violated.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem2'>This diagram gives an example where transformation of X can linearise a relationship.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem3'>In this example, transformation of Y both linearises the relationship and fixes non-constant variance.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem_c4'>This diagram shows how predictions of the response can be made from fitted model involving transformed response and explanatory variables.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem_c5'>This diagram shows how prediction intervals for the response can be found from a model fitted to transformed response and explanatory variables.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem6'>This diagram simulates data from a linear model and shows that about 5% of standardised residuals are outside +/-2 and very few are outside +/-3. However if the sample size is large, occasionally values a little outside +/-3 are seen.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem7'>This diagram shows that an outlier may not show up as a large residual if it is a high-leverage point.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem8'>A normal probability plot of residuals should be approximately normal if the model assumptions hold. In this page, simulations are used to assess curvature in probability plots for the residuals for 3 data sets. The reasons for the curvature are outliers, curvature and non-constant variance in the 3 examples.</page>
<page dir='en/regnProblem' filePrefix='l_regnProblem9'>This page does a simulation to help assess the Durbin-Watson statistic applied to the residuals from a linear model fitted to a time series.</page>

</section>
