<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Describing centre &amp;amp; spread'>

<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread1'>Example in which the differences between the centre and spread of two groups can be interpreted meaningfully. (The centre and spread of the second group can be changed with sliders.)</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread2'>Diagram similar to the previous one but showing that differences between the centres and spreads of the groups can be summarised by the median and either the range or inter-quartile range.</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread_c3'>Diagrams showing that median splits data set in half and mean is point of balance.</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread4'>Diagrams showing how mean is affected by an outlier and how it is further into the tail of a skew distribution.</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread5'>Diagram showing how the standard deviation reflects the spread of values in a data set. (The spread can be changed with a slider.)</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread6'>Examples illustrating the 70-95-100 rule of thumb for four data sets that are reasonably symmetric and also for another skew data set.</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread_c7'>A published table of means and sds for several variables in two groups is displayed. A diagram shows how sketched histograms can be drawn from the means and sds, showing the degree of overlap between the distributions in the two groups.</page>
<page dir='en/centerSpread' filePrefix='l_centerSpread8'>Diagram showing four data sets with the same mean and sd but differently shaped distributions (symmetric, a single outlier, two clusters, and skew). It shows that you must examine a graphical display, not just the mean and sd.</page>

</section>
