<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Continuous bivariate distributions">
<topText><![CDATA[<p>A full mathematical treatment of bivariate continuous distributions is beyond the scope of this course. In this section, we only sketch some of the concepts.</p>]]></topText>

<page dir="bk/massey200" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns1" summaryDir="bk/massey200" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns1" videoDir="en/bivarContinDistns" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarContinDistns1">Joint probability density functions describe the distributions of pairs of continuous random variables. Probabilities are defined as volumes under it.</page>
<page dir="bk/massey200" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns1a" summaryDir="bk/massey200" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns1a">Marginal and conditional distributions are conceptually similar for continuous and discrete random variables. You only need to understand the concepts but not derive them mathematically.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarContinDistns" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns2" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarContinDistns" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns2" videoDir="en/bivarContinDistns" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarContinDistns2">Probabilities can be found as double integrals of the joint probability density function.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarContinDistns" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns3" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarContinDistns" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns3" videoDir="en/bivarContinDistns" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarContinDistns3">The marginal distribution of one of the two variables is a univariate distribution whose pdf can be found by integrating the joint pdf over the other variable.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarContinDistns" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns4" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarContinDistns" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns4" videoDir="en/bivarContinDistns" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarContinDistns4">The conditional probability density function of one variable given the value of the other is the joint pdf divided by the marginal pdf of the other variable.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarContinDistns" filePrefix="bivarContinDistns5" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarContinDistns" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarContinDistns5" videoDir="en/bivarContinDistns" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarContinDistns5">As with discrete variables, continuous variables are independent if their joint pdf is the product of the two marginal pdfs. A random sample is a collection of n independent variables with the same distribution.</page>
</section>
