<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Bivariate normal distribution">
<topText><![CDATA[<p>The bivariate normal distribution is very important. You will need to know how to use it, but the proofs in this section will not be examined.</p>]]></topText>

<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal1" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal1" videoDir="en/bivarNormal" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarNormal1">The standard bivariate normal distribution has a single parameter, that affects the strength of the relationship between the variables. The joint pdf is given and the distribution's shape is described.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal2" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal2" videoDir="en/bivarNormal" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarNormal2">The general bivariate normal distribution is a generalisation with five parameters. Linear transformations of standard bivariate normal variables have this distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal3" note="Proof not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal3" videoDir="en/bivarNormal" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarNormal3">The marginal distributions are univariate normal distributions and their means and variances are four of the distribution's five parameters.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal4" note="Proof not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal4" videoDir="en/bivarNormal" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarNormal4">The conditional distribution of Y, given that X=x, is also a univariate normal distribution. Its shape is that of a slice through the joint pdf at x.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal5" note="Covariance proof not examined" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal5" videoDir="en/bivarNormal" videoFilePrefix="v_bivarNormal5">A formula is derived for the covariance of the two variables and their correlation is shown to be the fifth parameter of the bivariate normal distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/bivarNormal" filePrefix="bivarNormal6" summaryDir="en/bivarNormal" summaryFilePrefix="s_bivarNormal6">An example shows how the bivariate normal distribution can be used to find marginal and conditional probabilities.</page>
</section>
