<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="T distribution">

<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn1" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn1" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn1">The ratio of a standard normal variable and the square root of an independent chi-squared variable (divided by its degrees of freedom) has a t distribution. Its pdf is given.</page>
<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn2" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn2" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn2">Formulae for the mean and variance of the t distribution are given. Its tails are longer than those of a standard normal distribution, but the two distributions' shapes are close when the degrees of freedom are large.</page>
<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn3" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn3" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn3">A function of the sample mean, sample variance and μ is shown to have a t distribution if the sample comes from a normal distribution. It is a pivot for μ.</page>
<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn4" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn4" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn4">The pivot on the previous page can be used to find a confidence interval for a normal distribution's mean, μ.</page>
<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn5" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn5" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn5">The difference between two sample means from normal distributions is normally distributed. The &amp;quot;pooled&amp;quot; estimator of the common variance has a chi-squared distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/tDistn" filePrefix="tDistn6" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/tDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_tDistn6" videoDir="en/tDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_tDistn6">A pivot can be found from the difference between the sample means and pooled estimate of the variance. This can be used to find a confidence interval for the difference between the means.</page>
</section>
