<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Chi-squared distribution">

<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared1" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared1" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared1">The square of a variable with a standard normal distribution has a chi-squared distribution with one degree of freedom. It is a special case of a gamma distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared2" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared2" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared2">This chi-squared distribution is extremely skew. Its mean and variance are found from those of the gamma distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared3" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared3" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared3">The sum of n independent chi-squared variables (1 df) has a chi-squared (n df) distribution. It is also a special case of a gamma distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared4" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared4" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared4">The general chi-squared distribution with n degrees of freedom is also skew but becomes closer to symmetric when n increases. Its mean and variance are also given.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared5" note="Proof not examined" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared5" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared5">The variance of a random sample from a normal distribution has a distribution that is proportional to a chi-squared distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared6" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared6" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared6">A pivot can be based on a normal sample's variance. A confidence interval for the underlying normal distribution's variance σ² can be found from it.</page>
<page dir="en/chiSquared" filePrefix="chiSquared7" note="Optional" summaryDir="en/chiSquared" summaryFilePrefix="s_chiSquared7" videoDir="en/chiSquared" videoFilePrefix="v_chiSquared7">The sample variances from several normal random samples can be combined. If the underlying normal variances are equal, this pooled variance has a chi-squared distribution, allowing a confidence interval for σ² to be found.</page>
</section>
