<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Estimation">

<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation1" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation1" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation1">Thinking about how data arose often suggests a possible model for the values, but this usually involves one or more unknown values called parameters.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation2" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation2" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation2">The unknown parameters in a family of distributions may be estimated from a random sample, but there may be more than one way to do this from the data.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation3" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation3" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation3">An estimator is a function of a random sample and therefore has a distribution itself. Its bias is the difference between the distribution's mean and the actual parameter. An unbiased estimator is good.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation4" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation4" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation4">A good estimator's distribution should also have small spread. Its standard deviation is called the standard error of the estimator.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation5" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation5" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation5">The mean squared error of an estimator combines its bias and standard error into a single value that can be used to compare competing estimators.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation6" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation6" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation6">Most estimators that are based on random samples have bias and standard error that tend to zero as the sample size increases. Such estimators are called consistent.</page>
<page dir="en/estimation" filePrefix="estimation7" note="Not examined" summaryDir="en/estimation" summaryFilePrefix="s_estimation7" videoDir="en/estimation" videoFilePrefix="v_estimation7">The sample mean and median are compared as estimators of parameters from different families of distributions.</page>
</section>
