<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Confidence interval for mean">


<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean1" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean1" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean1">The estimation error for any unbiased estimator, has approximately 0.95 probability of being between -2SE and +2SE. An approximate 95% confidence interval for the parameter is therefore the estimate &amp;plusmn;2SE.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean2" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean2" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean2">If the population standard deviation is known, the standard error can be found exactly. A 95% confidence interval is the sample mean &amp;plusmn; twice this. (Or more exactly, 1.96 times the standard error.)</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean3" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean3" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean3">A simulation shows that 95% confidence intervals are random -- they vary from sample to sample. About 95% of samples give confidence intervals that include the true parameter.</page>

<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find approx 95% CI from standard error">This exercise displays an estimate and standard error and asks for an approximate 95% confidence interval. Various different types of parameters are estimated (not just means).</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find confidence intervals, known &amp;sigma;">This exercise gives practice with the calculations for finding the 95% confidence interval for a mean when the population standard deviation is known.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean7" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Interpret a 95% confidence interval">In this exercise, you must choose which of four statements correctly interprets the meaning of a 95% confidence interval.</page>

</section>
