<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="More about estimation">

<page dir="en/ciExtra" filePrefix="ciExtra1" summaryDir="en/ciExtra" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra1" videoDir="en/ciExtra" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra1">The margin of error for a survey is related to a confidence interval. It is close to a 95% CI when p is 0.5, but underestimates the accuracy of small or large sample proportions.</page>
<page dir="en/ciExtra" filePrefix="ciExtra2" summaryDir="en/ciExtra" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra2" videoDir="en/ciExtra" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra2">Given a target width for a 95% confidence interval, it is possible to determine the necessary sample size to achieve this accuracy.</page>
<page dir="en/ciExtra" filePrefix="ciExtra3" summaryDir="en/ciExtra" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra3" videoDir="en/ciExtra" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra3">In a similar way, given a target width for a 95% confidence interval for a proportion, it is possible to determine the necessary sample size.</page>
<page dir="en/ciExtra" filePrefix="ciExtra4" summaryDir="en/ciExtra" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra4" videoDir="en/ciExtra" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra4">All earlier confidence intervals had 95% confidence level. Replacing 1.96 (or 2) with other values gives interval estimates with different confidence levels.</page>

<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#CIs for &amp;micro; with other confidence levels">In this exercise, confidence intervals for a mean are requested with a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#CIs for &amp;pi; with other confidence levels">This exercise requests a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence intervals for a probability. A normal density can be used to find the relevant z-score and a template helps evaluate the 'plus-minus' value.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean6" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Factors affecting CI width of CI for &amp;micro;">This exercise asks how the sample size, sample standard deviation and confidence level affect the width of a CI for the mean.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Factors affecting width of CI for &amp;pi;">This exercise asks how the sample size, confidence level and population probability affect the width of a CI for the probability.</page>

</section>
