<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Standard deviation">


<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread5" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread5" videoDir="en/centerSpread" videoFilePrefix="v_centerSpread5">The standard deviation is the most commonly used numerical summary of the spread of values in a data set.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread6" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread6" videoDir="en/centerSpread" videoFilePrefix="v_centerSpread6">The 70-95-100 rule-of-thumb is useful for understanding the numerical value of the standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="centerSpread_c7" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread7" videoDir="en/centerSpread" videoFilePrefix="v_centerSpread7">It is possible to roughly guess the mean and standard deviation from a histogram and roughly sketch a symmetric histogram matching any given mean and standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="bk/ncea" filePrefix="centerSpread8" summaryDir="en/centerSpread" summaryFilePrefix="s_centerSpread8" videoDir="en/centerSpread" videoFilePrefix="v_centerSpread8">The mean and standard deviation cannot give any indication of the existance of outliers, skewness or clusters. A stem and leaf plot or histogram should be examined before reporting these numerical summaries.</page>

<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="e_centerSpread3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Standard deviation from graph">The first exercise asks for a rough 'guess' at the standard deviation of data sets from a stacked dot plot. The second exercise is similar but displays the data as a histogram or box plot.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="e_centerSpread4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Standard deviation from general knowledge">In this exercise, general knowledge about the type of measurement is enough to roughly guess the value of the standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/centerSpread" filePrefix="e_centerSpread5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Rough graph from mean and st devn">The mean and standard deviation of a data set should give you a good idea of the likely distribution of values. The first exercise in this page asks you to sketch a stacked dot plot to match a given mean and standard deviation. In the second, a histogram should be drawn.</page>

</section>
