<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Histograms and density">


<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density1" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density1" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density1">The heights of the stacks of leaves in a stem and leaf plot or crosses in a dot plot describe the density of values.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density2" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density2" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density2">In a simple histogram, the height of the rectangle above each class on the axis equals the number of values in the class -- the class frequency.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density3" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density3" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density3">Class width and start-point should be chosen to make the histogram as smooth as possible -- neither too blocky nor too jagged.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density4" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density4" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density4">The shape of a histogram can be very dependent on the choice of classes if the data set is small; beware over-interpreting its shape. Stacked dot plots are a better display of small data sets.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density6" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density6" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density6">The vertical axis should be relative frequency, not frequency, when comparing two groups with histograms. Population pyramids are often used to compare age distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density9" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density9" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density9">Frequency polygons are closely related to histograms but give a less 'blocky' display of density. Different groups can be compared more easily with them.</page>
<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="density11" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density11" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density11">Histograms are based on frequency tables. Class boundaries should avoid possible data values.</page>

<page dir="en/density" filePrefix="e_density1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a histogram">In this page, you will draw histograms of different data sets.</page>

</section>
