<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Linear model assumptions">

<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem1" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem1" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem1">The normal linear model involves assumptions of linearity, constant variance, normal error distribution and independence of different observations. Residuals can be examined to assess whether these assumptions are appropriate for a particular data set.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem2" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem2" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem2">If the relationship between Y and X is nonlinear, a transformation of X may linearise the relationship.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem3" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem3" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem3">Transforming the response may remove curvature in the relationship, but also affects whether the error standard deviation is constant. Fortunately, the same transformation of Y often removes curvature and non-constant standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem_c4" note="(advanced)" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem4" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem_c4">If a normal linear model describes the relationship between a transformation of the response and a transformation of the explanatory variable, predictions can be made by fitting the linear model to the transformed data, then performing the inverse transformation on the prediction.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem5" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem5" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem5">An outlier is a response value that is unusually large or small. An extreme residual suggests an outlier and standardised residuals can be used to assess it. However if the outlier corresponds to an extreme x-value (a high leverage point) it may not show up as a large residual.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem_c6" note="(optional)" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem6" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem_c6">The errors in a normal linear model are assumed to have normal distributions. Violation of this assumption is less important than nonlinearity, non-constant variance or outliers, but a probability plot of the residuals can be used to assess normality.</page>
<page dir="en/regnProblem" filePrefix="regnProblem7" note="(optional)" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem7" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem7">The errors in a normal linear model are assumed to be independent. In data where the observations are recorded sequentially, successive errors are sometimes found to be correlated. Correlated errors can arise whatever the x-variable, but are most often seen when the x-variable is time itself.</page>

</section>
