<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Changes over time'>

<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph0'>This page is an overview of the section.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph1'>Changes to a single numerical measurement over time can be displayed in a scatterplot of the measurement against time with successive values joined by lines.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph2'>If the measurement is a quantity, an alternative display is a bar chart with a bar for each successive value.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph3'>If the values at each time point form a partition of some total, such as a frequency table, a series of stacked bar charts of the values or proportions provides an effective display.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph4'>Simple time series are sometimes drawn in 3 dimensions as a ribbon chart. This may look more artistic, but makes the information in the data harder to see.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph5'>When presented on a computer, simple diagrams such as pie and bar charts can be animated to show how they change over time. However when the individual diagrams are simple, it is often possible to display all data in a static diagram more effectively. </page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph6'>Frequency tables of numerical measurements such as ages are usually displayed in histograms. They too can be animated to show changes over time.</page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph7'>A particularly useful type of display to animate is a scatterplot, either of crosses or circles of varying sizes. When the crosses represent countries or regions, it is often possible to pick out ones that behave differently from the rest. </page>
<page dir='en/timeGraph' filePrefix='timeGraph8'>Maps can also be animated to show changes over time. The measurement of interest can be displayed with either the shading of countries on the map or of circles that are superimposed on it.</page>

</section>
