<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Numerical factors'>


<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum1'>If the levels of the controlled factor are numerical values -- quantities of some numerical variable -- then we usually expect a 'smooth' relationship between the factor and response.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum2'>The simplest model for a smooth relationship between a numerical factor and response contains a linear term in the factor value. Adding a further quadratic term can model some curvature in the relationship.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum3'>Linear and quadratic models correspond to terms added to a model in which the factor does not affect the response. They can be equivalently defined through constraints on the smoothness of the parameters of the most general factor model.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum4'>The differences between the residual sum of squares of different models for a numerical factor called explained sums of squares and are have degrees of freedom equal to the difference between the unknown parameters of the models.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum5'>The explained and residual sums of squares can be presented in an analysis of variance table. The p-values can be used to test whether quadratic or linear relationships are consistent with the data.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum6'>If there are only two levels of the factor, a linear model is equivalent to a model with parameters for each level mean. Similarly, a quadratic model is equivalent to a this general factor model if there are three factor levels.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum7'>In any model with a numerical factor, its explained sum of squares can be split into linear and nonlinear components. The nonlinear sum of squares can be used to test whether the relationship is linear.</page>
<page dir='en/oneFactorNum' filePrefix='oneFactorNum8'>In some applications, we want to find the combination of values of two factors that optimises some response. A model with quadratic terms in the factors and an interaction term is often used.</page>

</section>
