<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Exercises for test 2'>
<topText><![CDATA[
		<p>The following exercises give you practice with the ten questions that will be asked in the second mastery test.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir='bk/massey120' filePrefix='e_scatterplot2' nameOverride='Interpret scatterplot'>The exercise in this page expects you to interpret scatterplots in terms of the relationship between the variables, clusters and outliers.</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='e_correlation1' nameOverride='Guess correlation'>In this exercise, you will make a rough estimate of correlation coefficient by eye from a scatterplot.</page>
<page dir='bk/massey120' filePrefix='e_leastSqrs3' nameOverride='Find equation of line'>The exercises on this page shows you a straight line and asks for its equation.</page>
<page dir='en/leastSqrs' filePrefix='e_leastSqrs5' nameOverride='Find a residual'>This exercise requests the least squares residual for a cross on a scatterplot.</page>
<page dir='en/leastSqrs' filePrefix='e_leastSqrs4' nameOverride='Interpret slope and intercept'>In this exercise, you are asked to select one of four statements that correctly describes the slope or intercept of a least squares line in the context of the data.</page>
<page dir='en/leastSqrs' filePrefix='e_leastSqrs7' nameOverride='Make prediction from LS line'>The exercise on this page gives a least squares line and asks for a prediction of the response, given the value of the explanatory variable.</page>
<page dir='bk/massey120' filePrefix='e_curvature1' nameOverride='Identify problems with LS line'>This exercise asks you to identify the difficulties with using the least squares line to predict Y at a given X from the data in a displayed scatterplot (an outlier, curvature, a high-leverage point or extrapolation).</page>
<page dir='en/timePlot' filePrefix='e_timePlot1' nameOverride='Identify patterns in a time series'>The exercise on this page asks you to identify whether a time series has trend, a seasonal pattern, a cyclic pattern or irregular variation.</page>
<page dir='en/smoothing' filePrefix='e_smoothing1' nameOverride='Find smoothed time series values'>This exercise asks you to evaluate an exponentially smoothed value and a moving average.</page>
<page dir='en/groupedCat' filePrefix='e_groupedCat2' nameOverride='Find proportion from contingency table'>In this exercise you are shown contingency tables and asked to find a joint, marginal or conditional proportion.</page>

</section>
