<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Standard error of mean">

<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean1" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean1" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean1">When using a sample mean to estimate a population mean, the errors have a distribution with mean zero. The standard deviation of the errors (standard error) is the standard deviation of the sample mean.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean2" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean2" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean2">If the population standard deviation is known, the standard error can be evaluated.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean3" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean3" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean3">The estimation error has about 95% probability of being within 2 standard errors of zero and is almost certainly within 3 standard errors.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean4" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean4" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean4">In most practical applications, the population standard deviation is unknown. The standard error of the sample mean can be approximated by replacing the population standard deviation by the sample standard deviation in its formula.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean5" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean5" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean5">It is important to distinguish between the interpretation (and value) of the standard error (SE) and standard deviation (SD).</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean6" nameOverride="Usng SEs to compare estimators" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean6" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean6">If there are two alternative estimators of a parameter, the estimator with lower standard error is usually better. The sample mean is shown to be a better estimator of the centre of a normal population than the sample median. </page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="seMean7" nameOverride="More about bias" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/seMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_seMean7" videoDir="en/seMean" videoFilePrefix="v_seMean7">Unbiased estimators are usually preferred. The sample median is shown to be a biased estimator of the mean of a skew distribution.</page>

</section>
