<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Other ways to present data">
<topText><![CDATA[<p>This section describes some novel ways to effectively display data. The complete section is optional and will not be examined.</p>]]></topText>

<page dir="en/scatterGraph" filePrefix="scatterGraph3" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/scatterGraph" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterGraph3">The crosses on a scatterplot can be coloured to distinguish different groups, or differing symbols can be used.</page>
<page dir="en/scatterGraph" filePrefix="scatterGraph4" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/scatterGraph" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterGraph4">Scatterplots are often used when the crosses correspond to different geographical regions. If these differ in size, the crosses can be replaced by circles whose area is proportional to the size &#151; e.g. area, population or GDP.</page>
<page dir="en/timeGraph" filePrefix="timeGraph7" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/timeGraph" summaryFilePrefix="s_timeGraph7">Changes over time can be animated and this is particularly useful for scatterplots. When the crosses represent countries or regions, it is often possible to pick out ones that behave differently from the rest. </page>
<page dir="en/maps" filePrefix="maps4" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/maps" summaryFilePrefix="s_maps4">Maps can have other simple bar and pie charts superimposed on each region. Only simple information about each region should be displayed in this way.</page>
<page dir="en/maps" filePrefix="maps5" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/maps" summaryFilePrefix="s_maps5">In most conventional maps, the areas of the regions are proportional to their land areas. The shapes of the regions can be distorted to make their areas proportional to their populations.</page>
<page dir="en/maps" filePrefix="maps6" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/maps" summaryFilePrefix="s_maps6">It is sometimes informative to distort a map to make the areas of regions proportional to other measurements. These measurements must be partitions of a meaningful total so that the combined measurement for two regions would be their total.</page>

</section>
