<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Probabilities from tables">
<topText><![CDATA[
	<p>Relationships between categorical variables (or other events) are described by probabilities.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir="en/prob" filePrefix="prob1" summaryDir="en/prob" summaryFilePrefix="s_prob1" videoDir="en/prob" videoFilePrefix="v_prob1">Bivariate categorical data are modelled as a sample from a population that consists of pairs of categorical values. The joint probability for any pair of categories is their population proportion.</page>
<page dir="en/prob" filePrefix="prob2" summaryDir="en/prob" summaryFilePrefix="s_prob2" videoDir="en/prob" videoFilePrefix="v_prob2">The marginal probabilities for a variable are the population proportions for its possible values. They can be found by summing joint probabilities.</page>
<page dir="en/prob" filePrefix="prob3" summaryDir="en/prob" summaryFilePrefix="s_prob3" videoDir="en/prob" videoFilePrefix="v_prob3">Conditional probabilites for a variable are proportions in a sub-population containing a specific value for the other variable. They are found by scaling the joint probabilities in that sub-population.</page>
<page dir="en/prob" filePrefix="prob4" summaryDir="en/prob" summaryFilePrefix="s_prob4" videoDir="en/prob" videoFilePrefix="v_prob4">Joint, marginal and conditional probabilities can be displayed graphically.</page>
<page dir="en/indep" filePrefix="indep1" summaryDir="en/indep" summaryFilePrefix="s_indep1" videoDir="en/indep" videoFilePrefix="v_indep1">Two categorical variables, X and Y, are associated (related) when the conditional distribution of Y given X=x is different for different values of x. Knowing the value of X therefore tells you something about Y.</page>
<page dir="en/indep" filePrefix="indep2" summaryDir="en/indep" summaryFilePrefix="s_indep2" videoDir="en/indep" videoFilePrefix="v_indep2">When the conditional distribution of Y is the same for all values of X, the variables are called independent. This special case is of practical importance.</page>

</section>
