<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Exercises">


<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="e_seMean1">The exercise on this page shows a data set with the sample mean and st devn. The standard error of the mean must be calculated.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="e_seMean2">This exercise gives the value of either the standard deviation or the standard error or the mean. The question asks for an interval containing about 95% of the values or an interval with 95% confidence of including the popn mean.</page>
<page dir="en/seMean" filePrefix="e_seMean3">This exercise asks 3 questions about the effect of sample size and spread of sample values on the sd and se, and about the interpretation of the se and sd.</page>

<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean1">This exercise displays an estimate and standard error and asks for an approximate 95% confidence interval. Various different types of parameters are estimated (not just means).</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean2" nameOverride="Find 95% CI for mean, known sigma">This exercise gives practice with the calculations for finding the 95% confidence interval for a mean when the population standard deviation is known.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean3" nameOverride="Find 95% CI for mean, unknown sigma">This exercise is similar to the previous one but requires use of a t distribution since the population standard deviation is unknown.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean6">This exercise asks how the sample size, sample standard deviation and confidence level affect the width of a CI for the mean.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean7">In this exercise, you must choose which of four statements correctly interprets the meaning of a 95% confidence interval.</page>

<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn1">A template is provided in this exercise to help evaluate the standard error of a sample proportion.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn2">This exercise gives practice at evaluating an approximate 95% confidence interval for a probability.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn4">This exercise asks how the sample size, confidence level and population probability affect the width of a CI for the probability.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn5">This exercise presents 3 different statements about a 95% confidence interval and asks which is correct.</page>

<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean4" nameOverride="CIs for mean at other confidence levels, known sigma">In this exercise, confidence intervals are requested with a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence levels, but with known population standard deviation.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean5">In this exercise, the questions involve a mixture of types with known and unknown population standard deviation and with 90%, 95% and 99% confidence levels.</page>

<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn3" nameOverride="CIs for proportions, various confidence levels">This exercise requests a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence intervals for a probability. A normal density can be used to find the relevant z-score and a template helps evaluate the 'plus-minus' value.</page>


</section>
