<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Inference'>


<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro1'>Assessing whether a categorical factor affects the response must take into account both variation between the treatment means and also variation within each factor level.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro2'>For experiments with numerical factors, the ideas of between- and within-treatment variation must be generalised to explained and unexplained variation. Both types of variation affect our assessment of whether the factor affects the response.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro3'>Explained and unexplained variation are summarised by quantities called explained and unexplained sums of squares.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro4'>The explained and unexplained sums of squares form the basis of an analysis of variance table that can be used to test whether the factor really does affect the response.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro5'>A linear model is the simplest one for a numerical factor but a quadratic model and one that treats the factor as categorical categorical allow increasing degrees of curvature in the relationship. Models that allow curvature have smaller residual sums of squares.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro6'>The explained sum of squares for changing from a quadratic to a categorical model is the basis of an anova test of goodness-of-fit of a quadratic model. The explained sum of squares for changing from a linear to a quadratic model can be used to test for curvature.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro7'>The mean residual sum of squares estimates the variance of the 'errors' in the model. This is also the variance of replicate observations within any factor level.</page>
<page dir='en/anovaIntro' filePrefix='anovaIntro8'>Confidence intervals for the treatment means provide a good summary of the effect of a factor.</page>

</section>
