<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Designs for 4 and 8 runs'>
<topText><![CDATA[
	<p>In factorial experiments, we can estimate the main effects of <em>n</em> 
    factors in 2<em><sup>n</sup></em> runs. This section introduces related experimental 
    designs for <strong>more</strong> than <em>n</em> factors called <strong>fractional 
    </strong>factorial experiments<strong> </strong>. Most practical experiments 
    involve 8 or more runs but the concepts are first introduced for experiments 
    with only 4 runs.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design1'>One replicate of a complete factorial experiment for 2 factors requires 4 runs. The two factors and their interaction are orthogonal, so all effects can be independently estimated. </page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design2'>If the levels for C are defined by the AB interaction term in a complete factorial experiment for A and B, all three factors are orthogonal. However the main effects are confounded with 2-factor interactions.</page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design3'>Since main effects are confounded with 2-factor interactions in a fractional factorial experiment for 3 factors in 4 runs, the interactions must be assumed to be negligible before the main effects can be used to rank the importance of the factors.</page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design4'>Two replicates of a complete factorial experiment with 2 factors or one replicate of a complete factorial experiment with 3 factors can be conducted in 8 runs. All main effects and interactions can be estimated.</page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design5'>A fractional factorial experiment for 4 factors in 8 runs can be designed by confounding D with the ABC interaction. Main effects are not confounded with 2-factor interactions but 2-factor interactions are confounded with each other.</page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design6'>A design with up to seven orthogonal factors can be defined by confounding D, E, F and G with the three 2-factor interactions and the 3-factor interaction in a complete factorial experiment for A, B and C. Main effects are confounded with 2-factor interactions.</page>
<page dir='en/run48Design' filePrefix='run48Design7'>Importance of factors is determined by their main effects. However this ranking assumes that 2-factor interactions are negligible if there are 5 or more factors.</page>

</section>
