<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Independence'>
<topText><![CDATA[
	<p>Relationships between categorical variables can be described in similar terms to these used for numerical variables.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep1'>Two categorical variables, X and Y, are associated (related) when the conditional distribution of Y given X=x is different for different values of x. Knowing the value of X therefore tells you something about Y.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep2'>When the conditional distribution of Y is the same for all values of X, the variables are called independent. This special case is of practical importance.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep3'>Independence is a population property. To assess independence from a sample contingency table, the observed cell counts are compared to those estimated from a model with independence.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep4'>The raw sum of squared differences between observed and estimated cell counts is not a good test statistic.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep5'>The 'chi-squared' statistic is a modified sum of squared differences that has a standard distribution (a chi-squared distribution) when there is independence.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep6'>The chi-squared statistic can be used to find a p-value for testing independence. The p-value has similar interpretation and properties to p-values for all other hypothesis tests.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep7'>The chi-squared test is applied to a few real data sets. When the variables are found to be associated, the nature of the relationship is described from a comparison of observed and estimated cell counts.</page>
<page dir='gd/indep' filePrefix='indep8'>The chi-squared test assesses independence of two categorical variables. It is also used to test whether a single categorical variable has the same distribution in several groups.</page>

</section>
