<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Randomised blocks'>


<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock1'>In some data sets, the values arise in blocks of 3 or more related measurements. Randomised block and repeated measure data are of this form.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock2'>Ignoring the blocking of values loses important information about the difference between treatments. Comparing treatments separately against a baseline treatment using paired differences may be possible.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock3'>If there is no baseline treatment against which to compare the other measurements in each block, it is possible to simultaneously test whether all treatment means are equal. Again, ignoring the blocks loses important information.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock4'>Data of this form often arises from a randomised block experiment in which the experimental units occur in related blocks and treatments are randomly allocated within each block.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock5' note='(optional)'>Although blocks and treatments arise in different ways, they are modelled similarly. A 3-dimensional display of the data represents both blocks and treatments in the same way.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock6'>The variation between blocks can be removed by adding/subtracting a value to each block to make all block means equal. This reduces the residual (unexplained) sum of squares.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock7'>The total sum of squares can be split into sums of squares for blocks and treatments, and a residual sum of squares.</page>
<page dir='gd/randBlock' filePrefix='randBlock8'>An anova table shows these sums of squares and associated degrees of freedom. The F-ratio for treatments in the table is the basis of a test for equal treatment means. Several examples are given.</page>

</section>
