<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Tests about proportions">


<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn1" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn1" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn1">When the data are a random sample, the null and alternative hypotheses are usually expressed in terms of population parameters. For categorical samples, the hypotheses refer to the probabilities of the categories.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn2" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn2" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn2">The p-value for testing a proportion is the probability of getting such an 'extreme' number of successes when the null hypothesis holds. It can be found from the binomial distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn3" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn3" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn3">An example shows how to use a binomial distribution to find the p-value for a test.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn4" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn4" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn4">If values in both tails of the binomial distribution support the alternative hypothesis, the tail probability must be doubled to give the p-value for the test.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn5" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn5" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn5">When the sample size is large, a normal approximation to the binomial distribution can be used to find the p-value for a hypothesis test.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn6" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn6" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn6">The statistical distance between an estimate and hypothesised parameter value is the difference divided by the standard error of the estimate. It should have approximately a standard normal distribution if the null hypothesis is true.</page>
<page dir="en/testPropn" filePrefix="testPropn7" summaryDir="en/testPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn7" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn7">The p-value for testing a proportion can be evaluated as a tail area of a standard normal distribution corresponding to values more 'extreme' than the statistical distance between p and π.</page>

</section>
