<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Two or more factors">

<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo1" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo1" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo1">A second factor can be varied in a randomised experiment for one factor without affecting the accuracy of the estimated effect of the first factor.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo2" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo2" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo2">In a factorial experiment, each combination of the levels of two or more factors is used on the same number of experimental units.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo3" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo3" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo3">The simplest model for the effect of two factors assumes that the effect of each factor is the same, whatever the value of the other factor. The mean response can be written as the sum of the effects of the separate factors.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo4" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo4" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo4">If the effect of one factor depends on the level of the other, there is said to be interaction between them. Interaction can be assessed from a factorial experiment.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo5" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo5" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo5">This example helps to explain the concept of interaction.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo6" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo6" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo6">The simplest model for three or more factors assumes that the effect of each does not depend on the levels of the others. The mean response is modelled as the sum of terms for the individual factors.</page>
<page dir="en/designTwo" filePrefix="designTwo7" summaryDir="en/designTwo" summaryFilePrefix="s_designTwo7" videoDir="en/designTwo" videoFilePrefix="v_designTwo7">In factorial experiments with 3 or more factors, there may be interactions between two or more of the factors.</page>

</section>
