<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Probability &amp;amp; probability density">

<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity1" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity1" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity1">When randomly selecting one value from a population of N different values, the probability of getting any individual value is 1/N. More generally, the probability of sampling a value in any range is the proportion of population values in the range.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity2" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity2" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity2">The probability of any type of value is again the proportion of such values in the population. It can also be interpreted as the limiting proportion from a sample of values if the sample size is increased indefinitely.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity3" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity3" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity3">Infinite categorical or discrete populations can be described by bar charts of the probabilities.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity4" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity4" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity4">Infinite continuous numerical populations are described with a type of histogram called a probability density function.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity5" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity5" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity5">Normal distributions are infinite continuous populations. A normal distribution is symmetric and its two parameters, &amp;micro; and &amp;sigma;, can be adjusted to alter the distribution's location and spread.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity6" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity6" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity6">When a value is sampled from an infinite continuous population, the probability that it is between a and b equals the area under the p.d.f. between these two values.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity7" note="(optional)" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity7" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity7">This page describes some rules that are obeyed by probabilities.</page>

</section>
