<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Simulation (optional)">

<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim1" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim1" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim1">Probability can be used to model complex situations. A simulation of the model involves using the model's probabilities to generate an instance of the situation. Repeating the simulation can give insight into the behaviour of the system.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim2" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim2" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim2">A simulation demonstrates that the best team is often not top of a league at the end of the season even if it has a much higher probability of winning individual matches than all other teams.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim3" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim3" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim3">A simulation of a soccer league shows that the spread of points at the end of an actual soccer season is not consistent with all teams having equal abilities.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim4" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim4" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim4">The variability of displays from 'regular' populations (such as normal distributions) can be used to assess features in a single data set, such as outliers, clusters or skewness.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim5" note="(advanced)" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim5" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim5">Simulations are based on randomly generated values. These are generally based on random numbers for which any value between 0 and 1 is equally likely.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim6" note="(advanced)" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim6" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim6">A random categorical value can be easily generated from a random number between 0 and 1.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="probSim7" note="(advanced)" summaryDir="en/probSim" summaryFilePrefix="s_probSim7" videoDir="en/probSim" videoFilePrefix="v_probSim7">Generating random numerical values from a particular distribution is harder. This page describes one such method.</page>

</section>
