<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Comparing several means'>


<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup1'>This is a 3-dimensional diagram of normal distributions in 3 groups. The normal parameters can be changed (with sliders) and their standard deviations can be constrained to be equal. Samples from the model can be selected and displayed.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup2'>This diagram illustrates the formula for the pooled estimate of the common variance. The group sizes can be the same or can be different.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup_b3'>This page shows a few examples of 95% CIs for the difference between two group means. The calculations are done both with a pooled estimate of the sd and with separate estimates from the two groups.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup4'>The diagram on this page allows variation between and within groups to be altered with sliders. It is used to explain that the strongest evidence of a difference is when between-group variation is large and within-group variation is small.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup5'>This diagram explains the total, between-groups and within-groups sums of squares by drawing lines on the scatterplot for each whose sum of squares gives the ssq. The proportion of explained variation can be altered with a slider.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup_b6'>A few examples show how R-squared is calculated from the analysis of variance table and give its interpretation.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup7'>This diagram shows data from several groups and the corresponding analysis of variance table. The proportion of explained variation can be adjusted with a slider, showing how the F-ratio and p-value change.</page>
<page dir='en/multiGroup' filePrefix='l_multiGroup_b8'>In this page, the F-test is applied to a few data sets and the resulting p-value is interpreted.</page>

</section>
