<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Inference for regression parameters">


<page dir="en/regnEst" filePrefix="regnEst_c1" summaryDir="en/regnEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnEst1" videoDir="en/regnEst" videoFilePrefix="v_regnEst_c1">A least squares line provides estimates of the linear model's slope and intercept. These estimates are random values — they vary from sample to sample.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnEst_c2" summaryDir="en/regnEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnEst2" videoDir="en/regnEst" videoFilePrefix="v_regnEst_c2">The third parameter of the normal linear model is the error standard deviation. It can be estimated using the residuals from the least squares line.</page>
<page dir="en/regnEst" filePrefix="regnEst3" summaryDir="en/regnEst" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnEst3" videoDir="en/regnEst" videoFilePrefix="v_regnEst3">The least squares estimate of the model's slope has a normal distribution that is centred on the true value.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnEst_c4" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnEst4" videoDir="en/regnEst" videoFilePrefix="v_regnEst_c4">The distribution of the least squares slope may be estimated from a single data set.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnTest_c2" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnTest2" videoDir="en/regnTest" videoFilePrefix="v_regnTest_c2">If the model's slope is zero, the response distribution does not depend on the explanatory variable. The p-value for testing this is the probability that its least squares estimate is as far from zero as the recorded value.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnTest3" summaryDir="en/regnTest" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnTest3" videoDir="en/regnTest" videoFilePrefix="v_regnTest3">It is important to distinguish the strength of a relationship (summarised by the correlation coefficient) and the strength of evidence for existence of a relationship (summarised by the p-value).</page>

<page dir="en/regnEst" filePrefix="e_regnEst1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise:#+#  Standard error of slope">Any estimator's standard error gives information about its accuracy. The exercise on this page gives the standard error of a least squares line's slope and asks for a roughly calculated interval that is likely to include the underlying model's slope. (T values are not required in this exercise.)</page>
<page dir="en/regnEst" filePrefix="e_regnEst2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise:#+#  Confidence interval for slope">In the two exercises on this page, confidence intervals for a regression model's slope should be calculated from the least squares slope and its standard error. The second exercise is a little harder -- it asks for various confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/regnTest" filePrefix="e_regnTest1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise:#+#  Test for zero slope">This exercise gives the least squares slope and its standard error. The p-value for testing whether the regression slope is zero should be calculated and interpreted.</page>
</section>
