<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Conditional probability">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb1" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb1" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_conditProb1">For data with two categorical variables we summarise frequencies for each combination of categories in a contingency table.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb2" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb2" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_conditProb2">Bivariate categorical data are modelled as a sample from a population that consists of pairs of categorical values. The joint probability for any pair of categories is their population proportion.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb3" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb3" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_conditProb3">The marginal probabilities for a variable are the population proportions for its possible values. They can be found by summing joint probabilities.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb4" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb4" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_conditProb4">Conditional probabilites for a variable are proportions in a sub-population containing a specific value for the other variable. They are found by scaling the joint probabilities in that sub-population.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb5" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb5" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_conditProb5">Joint, marginal and conditional probabilities can be displayed graphically.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb6" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb6">A tree diagram is another device useful for displaying and calculating conditional and joint probabilities. A situation summarised in a table of joint probabilities can be represented in tree diagram form, and vice versa.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="conditProb7" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_conditProb7">We can use a tree diagram for any situation that involves a sequence of events.</page>

<page dir="en/groupedCat" filePrefix="e_groupedCat2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find contingency table proportions">In this exercise you are shown contingency tables and asked to find a joint, marginal or conditional proportion.</page>

</section>
