<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Normal distribution calculations">


<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="normalDistn5" summaryDir="en/normalDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_normalDistn5" videoDir="en/normalDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_normalDistn5">Any value, x, can be translated into a z-score that gives the number of standard deviations above the mean.</page>
<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="normalDistn_c6" summaryDir="en/normalDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_normalDistn6" videoDir="en/normalDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_normalDistn6">Z-scores have a standard normal distribution (mean 0 and s.d. 1). The probability of a value less than x can be translated into a probability about a z-score.</page>
<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="normalDistn_c7" summaryDir="en/normalDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_normalDistn7" videoDir="en/normalDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_normalDistn_c7">The probability that X is greater than a specified value or is between two values can also be translated into a probability about a z-score.</page>
<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="normalDistn8" nameOverride="Normal tables" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/normalDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_normalDistn8" videoDir="en/normalDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_normalDistn8">If a computer is not available, tables of probabilities for the standard normal distribution are used to find normal probabilities.</page>
<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="normalDistn9" summaryDir="en/normalDistn" summaryFilePrefix="s_normalDistn9" videoDir="en/normalDistn" videoFilePrefix="v_normalDistn9">The inverse problem of finding the x-value corresponding to a given probability is also solved using z-scores. If normal tables are used, they must be looked up differently.</page>

<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="e_normalDistn2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Probability and area under pdf">Exercise asks for a normal probability by reading an area under a normal histogram (pdf).</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="e_normalDistn3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Probabilities from z-scores">The exercise on this page is similar to the previous exercise, but the question must be first translated into one involving a z-score. The required probability is read off a standard normal histogram (pdf).</page>
<page dir="en/normalDistn" filePrefix="e_normalDistn4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Expected count in sample">Instead of the probability of getting a value within some range, the questions in this exercise ask for the expected number out of n items. </page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="e_normalDistn5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find X from probability">The exercise on this page asks the inverse problem; given a probability, it ask for the corresponding range of values using a standard normal histogram (pdf). </page>

</section>
