<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Linear model assumptions">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnProblem1" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem1" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem1">The normal linear model involves assumptions of linearity, constant variance, normal error distribution and independence of different observations. Residuals can be examined to assess whether these assumptions are appropriate for a particular data set.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="leastSqrs6" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_leastSqrs6" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_leastSqrs6">Outliers and curvature in the relationship are often displayed more clearly in a plot of residuals.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnProblem6" summaryDir="en/regnProblem" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem6" videoDir="en/regnProblem" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem6">Curvature in a probability plot of residuals can indicate problems with the model. Curvature can be caused by a non-normal error distribution but may also result from other problems with the model.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="leastSqrs5" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_leastSqrs5" videoDir="en/leastSqrs" videoFilePrefix="v_leastSqrs5">An outlier is a response value that is unusually large or small.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnProblem5" nameOverride="Standardised residuals" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnProblem5" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_regnProblem5">An extreme residual suggests an outlier and standardised residuals can be used to assess it.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnLeverage" nameOverride="Outliers and leverage" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnLeverage" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_regnLeverage">If an outlier corresponds to an extreme x-value (a high leverage point) it may not show up as a large residual.</page>

<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs6" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Pick the correct residual plot">In this exercise, you must identify which of four scatterplots is the correct residual plot when a linear model is fitted to a data set.</page>
<page dir="en/curvature" filePrefix="e_curvature1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Identify regression problems" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)">This exercise asks you to identify the difficulties with using the least squares line to predict Y at a given X from the data in a displayed scatterplot (an outlier, curvature, a high-leverage point or extrapolation).</page>

</section>
