<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Estimating proportions">


<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn1" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn1" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn1">The methodology for describing the accuracy of a sample mean using standard errors and confidence intervals can also be used for other parameter estimates.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn2" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn2" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn2">A sample proportion estimates the corresponding population proportion, &amp;pi;. There is likely to be an error in this estimate and these errors have a distribution.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="estPropn_c3" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn3" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c3">The estimation errors have a type of binomial distribution that is scaled to have mean zero. Its standard deviation is the standard error of the proportion.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="estPropn_c4" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn_c4" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c4">If the sample size is high enough, the error distribution is approximately normal. This page gives a few examples for which the error distribution is found.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="estPropn_c5" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn5" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c5">A 95% confidence interval for a population proportion is the sample proportion &amp;plusmn; 1.96 times its standard deviation. Its confidence level is only approximately 95% and guidelines are given for the minimum sample size.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="ciExtra4b" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra4b">Replacing 1.96 with other values gives interval estimates with different confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="estPropn6" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn6" videoDir="en/estPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn6">If samples are repeatedly taken, about 95% of them result in 95% confidence intervals that include the population proportion. Guidelines are given for the minimum sample size to make the confidence level close to 95%.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="estPropn_c7" summaryDir="en/estPropn" summaryFilePrefix="s_estPropn_c7" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_estPropn_c7">A 95% confidence intervals for a proportion are found and interpreted for several data sets.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="ciExtra1" summaryDir="en/ciExtra" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra1" videoDir="en/ciExtra" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra1">The margin of error for a survey is related to a confidence interval. It is close to a 95% CI when p is 0.5, but underestimates the accuracy of small or large sample proportions.</page>

<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find standard error of proportion">A template is provided in this exercise to help evaluate the standard error of a sample proportion.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find CI for probability">This exercise requests a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence intervals for a probability. A normal density can be used to find the relevant z-score and a template helps evaluate the 'plus-minus' value.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#What affects width of CI?">This exercise asks how the sample size, confidence level and population probability affect the width of a CI for the probability.</page>
<page dir="en/estPropn" filePrefix="e_estPropn5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Interpret a 95% confidence interval">This exercise presents 3 different statements about a 95% confidence interval and asks which is correct.</page>

</section>
