<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Confidence interval for mean">


<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean_c1" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean1" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean_c1">The estimation error for any unbiased estimator, has approximately 0.95 probability of being between -2SE and +2SE. An approximate 95% confidence interval for the parameter is therefore the estimate &amp;plusmn;2SE.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean2" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean2" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean2">If the population standard deviation is known, the standard error can be found exactly. A 95% confidence interval is the sample mean &amp;plusmn; twice this. (Or more exactly, 1.96 times the standard error.)</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean3" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean3" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean3">A simulation shows that 95% confidence intervals are random — they vary from sample to sample. About 95% of samples give confidence intervals that include the true parameter.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean4" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean4" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean4">In practice, the population standard deviation is usually unknown. If the population sd is simply replaced by its sample equivalent, the interval estimate has a lower confidence level than 95%.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean5" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean5" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean5">To get a 95% confidence level, a t-value from tables must replace the constant 1.96.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean6" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean6" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean6">A simulation demonstrates that the resulting 95% confidence intervals have probability 0.95 of including the population mean.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="ciExtra4a" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciExtra4a" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_ciExtra4a">All earlier confidence intervals had 95% confidence level. Replacing 1.96 (or a value from t tables) with other values gives interval estimates with different confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="ciMean_c7" summaryDir="en/ciMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_ciMean_c7" videoDir="en/ciMean" videoFilePrefix="v_ciMean_c7">Some examples of 95% confidence intervals for population means are given and interpreted.</page>

<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find approx 95% CI from standard error">This exercise displays an estimate and standard error and asks for an approximate 95% confidence interval. Various different types of parameters are estimated (not just means).</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find confidence intervals, known &amp;sigma;">In this exercise, confidence intervals are requested with a mixture of 90%, 95% and 99% confidence levels, but with known population standard deviation</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find CIs, known and unknown &amp;sigma;">In this exercise, the questions involve a mixture of types with known and unknown population standard deviation and with 90%, 95% and 99% confidence levels.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean6" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#What affects width of confidence interval">This exercise asks how the sample size, sample standard deviation and confidence level affect the width of a CI for the mean.</page>
<page dir="en/ciMean" filePrefix="e_ciMean7" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Interpret a 95% confidence interval">In this exercise, you must choose which of four statements correctly interprets the meaning of a 95% confidence interval.</page>

</section>
