<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Comparing groups">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="displayInterp5" summaryDir="en/displayInterp" summaryFilePrefix="s_displayInterp5" videoDir="en/displayInterp" videoFilePrefix="v_displayInterp5">If the values come from 2 or more groups of individuals, dot plots and stem and leaf plots can be modified to show this extra information.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="density_c6" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density6" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density_c6">The vertical axis should be relative frequency, not frequency, when comparing two groups with histograms. Population pyramids are often used to compare age distributions.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="density_c9" summaryDir="en/density" summaryFilePrefix="s_density9" videoDir="en/density" videoFilePrefix="v_density_c9">Frequency polygons are closely related to histograms but give a less 'blocky' display of density. Different groups can be compared more easily with them.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="boxPlot1" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot1" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot1">Dot plots, stem and leaf plots and histograms contain detailed information that is distracting when two or more data sets are being compared.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="boxPlot2" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot2" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot2">The median and quartiles split a batch of values into four equal-sized sets of values. A box plot is a graphical display of the median, quartiles and extremes.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="boxPlot3" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot3" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot3">A box plot clearly shows the centre, spread and skewness of a data set. It splits the corresponding histogram into 4 approximately equal areas.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="boxPlot4" nameOverride="Displaying outliers" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot4" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot4">The basic box plot is often modified to display outliers as separate crosses.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="boxPlot5" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot5" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot5">Box plots cannot show clusters, so should not be used to summarise data with clusters.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="boxPlot_c6" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot6" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot_c6">Box plots are particularly effective for displaying differences between several groups of values.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="boxPlot7" summaryDir="en/boxPlot" summaryFilePrefix="s_boxPlot7" videoDir="en/boxPlot" videoFilePrefix="v_boxPlot7">Box plots are relatively stable, and contain less 'noise' than other displays. They can concisely describe differences between even small groups.</page>

<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="e_boxPlot1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a box plot">The exercises on this page involve drawing box plots from sorted lists of values. For the second (optional) exercise, 'outliers' must be separately identified.</page>
<page dir="en/boxPlot" filePrefix="e_boxPlot2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Shape of a box plot">The exercises on this page involve matching the shape of box plots to the corresponding dot plots.</page>

</section>
