<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Introduction to hypothesis testing">


<page dir="en/testIntro" filePrefix="testIntro1" summaryDir="en/testIntro" summaryFilePrefix="s_testIntro1" videoDir="en/testIntro" videoFilePrefix="v_testIntro1">Estimation asks which values for an unknown parameter are consistent with data that have been collected. Hypothesis testing usually asks whether the data are consistent with some parameter values.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testIntro2" summaryDir="en/testIntro" summaryFilePrefix="s_testIntro2" videoDir="en/testIntro" videoFilePrefix="v_testIntro2">Are some teams in a soccer league better than others, or is the end-of-season league table consistent with random results from equally-matched teams? A simulation can help to answer this question.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testIntro_c3" summaryDir="en/testIntro" summaryFilePrefix="s_testIntro3" videoDir="en/testIntro" videoFilePrefix="v_testIntro_c3">This page presents a simulation to test whether the number of observations observed in one category is consistent with a specified probability.</page>
<page dir="en/testIntro" filePrefix="testIntro4" nameOverride="Test for a mean" summaryDir="en/testIntro" summaryFilePrefix="s_testIntro4" videoDir="en/testIntro" videoFilePrefix="v_testIntro4">A simulation is used to test whether a sample mean is consistent with a specified population mean.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testIntro_c7" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_testIntro_c7" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_testIntro_c7">All hypothesis tests involve a null hypothesis, a test statistic, an alternative hypothesis and a p-value.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testPropn6" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn6" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn6">The statistical distance between an estimate and hypothesised parameter value is the difference divided by the standard error of the estimate. It should have approximately a standard normal distribution if the null hypothesis is true.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testPropn7" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_testPropn7" videoDir="en/testPropn" videoFilePrefix="v_testPropn7">When testing a single parameter, we often use a test statistic that 'standardises' an estimate of the parameter — subtracting the hypothesised value and dividing by its standard error. This test statistic describes the statistical distance of the estimate from the null hypothesis value and has a distribution that is close to a standard normal distribution.</page>

<page dir="en/testIntro" filePrefix="e_testIntro1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Simulation to test a propn" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)">This exercise asks you to perform a simulation to test a hypothesis about a population proportion, &amp;pi;.</page>
<page dir="en/testIntro" filePrefix="e_testIntro2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Simulation to test a mean" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)">This exercise is similar but the simulation is from a normal population and tests the value of its mean, &amp;micro;.</page>

</section>
