<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Tests about means">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testMean_c1" summaryDir="en/testMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean1" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_testMean1">For numerical populations, the null and alternative hypotheses usually specify values for the population mean. Tests are based on the sample mean.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="testMean_c2" summaryDir="en/testMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean2" videoDir="en/testMean" videoFilePrefix="v_testMean_c2">If the population standard deviation is known, the distribution of the sample mean can be found when the null hypothesis is true. The p-value for the test is a tail area of this distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="testMean3" summaryDir="en/testMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean3" videoDir="en/testMean" videoFilePrefix="v_testMean3">The p-value is most easily found from the 'statistical distance' between the sample and hypothesised means. The p-value can be found as a tail area of the standard normal distribution and is approximately correct even when the population distribution is not normal.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="testMean_c4" summaryDir="en/testMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean4" videoDir="en/testMean" videoFilePrefix="v_testMean_c4">When the population standard deviation is unknown, a different test statistic must be used. It has a standard distribution known as a t distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="testMean_c5" summaryDir="en/testMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean5" videoDir="en/testMean" videoFilePrefix="v_testMean_c5">The t distribution is used to obtain a p-value for tests about a population mean when the standard deviation is unknown.</page>

<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="testMean6" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_testMean6">The t-test is based on an assumption that the population distribution is normally distributed. It can also be used with non-normal populations provided the sample size is large but should not be used to test the mean of a small sample if the distribution is skew.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="e_testMean1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#  Test mean, with &amp;sigma; known">This exercise asks you to perform a hypothesis test about the mean of a normal population whose standard deviation, σ, is known. The hypotheses must be specified, a z-score evaluated, the p-value found and the conclusion given.</page>
<page dir="en/testMean" filePrefix="e_testMean2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#  Test mean, unknown &amp;sigma;">In this exercise, the population standard deviation is unknown, so the test statistic must use the sample standard deviation and the p-value must be looked up from a t distribution.</page>

</section>
