<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Bar and pie charts">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="univarCat1" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat1" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat1">A bar chart displays the frequencies in a frequency table graphically.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="univarCat2" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat2" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat2">For barcharts of categorical data whose categories have no natural ordering, it is often helpful to sort the categories into decreasing frequencies.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="univarCat3" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat3" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat3">The temptation to embellish simple barcharts should be resisted. Some such 'artistic' embellishments are misleading.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="univarCat_c4" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat4" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat_c4">These are alternatives to a bar chart for categorical data.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="univarCat_c5" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat5" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat_c5">Bar charts distinguish better the proportions in single categories. Pie charts are better for showing the proportion in a groups of categories.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="univarCat_c6" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat_c6" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat_c6">Three-dimensional pie charts are often drawn. If a pie chart holds little information, it is better to draw it small than to enhance it in this way.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="univarCat7" nameOverride="Bar &amp; pie charts for quantities" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/univarCat" summaryFilePrefix="s_univarCat7" videoDir="en/univarCat" videoFilePrefix="v_univarCat7">Bar and pie charts can be used to display any data where a total quantity is split into parts.</page>

<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a bar chart">In this exercise, you will draw the bar chart corresponding to a frequency table.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find proportion from bar chart">This exercise shows bar charts for data sets with ordered categories, augmented with a graph of the cumulative frequencies. You are asked to find proportions and percentages from the diagram.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Pareto diagram">In this exercise, you will produce a Pareto diagram by reordering the bars of a bar chart, then find a proportion or percentage relating to the most important or least important categories.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a pie chart">In this exercise, you will draw the pie chart corresponding to a frequency table, using either the individual frequencies or the cumulative frequencies.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Match bar and pie charts">Bar and pie charts display the same information in different ways. This exercise displays bar and pie charts for four data sets and asks you to match them.</page>
<page dir="en/univarCat" filePrefix="e_univarCat6" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Proportions from pie chart">This exercise displays the pie chart for either an ordinal categorical variable or a categorical variable in which the categories have been arranged in decreasing order of their frequencies. You are asked to estimate the percentage in some adjacent categories 'by eye' from the pie chart.</page>

</section>
