<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Sampling in practice">
<topText><![CDATA[<p>In many practical situations, there are better sampling schemes than simple  random samples. Whatever the sampling scheme, non-sampling errors can badly affect  results.</p>]]></topText>


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice1" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice1" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice1">More accurate estimates can sometimes be obtained by taking separate random samples within different parts of the population.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice2" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice2" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice2">When individuals are grouped in clusters, it is often cheaper to sample complete clusters rather than separate individuals.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice3" nameOverride="Two-stage sampling" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice3" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice3">When the target population is spread over a wide area, it may be cheaper to take a sample from only a few regions (groups of individuals), than to sample from all the regions.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice8" nameOverride="Cost &amp; accuracy of sampling schemes" note="Optional (not examined)#(opt)" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice8" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice8">A stratified random sample is usually more accurate than a simple random sample of the same size. Cluster and two-stage samples are less accurate but can reduce costs considerably.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice9" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice9">It is often easier to sample individuals who are regularly spaced in a list (e.g. every tenth individual) rather than randomly sampling from the whole list. In a systematic sample, only the first individual is randomly chosen.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice4" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice4" videoDir="en/sampPractice" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice4">Samples are usually collected to estimate population characteristics. The ordinary variation caused by the sampling scheme is called sampling error. Practical difficulties with conducting the survey can cause biased estimates (non-sampling errors).</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice5" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice5" videoDir="en/sampPractice" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice5">Coverage error and non-response error prevent some individuals being included in the sample.</page>
<page dir="en/sampPractice" filePrefix="sampPractice6" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice6" videoDir="en/sampPractice" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice6">Interviewer error and instrument error can result in 'incorrect' measurements from the sampled individuals.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="sampPractice7" summaryDir="en/sampPractice" summaryFilePrefix="s_sampPractice7" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_sampPractice7">Survey information is collected by a variety of mechanisms, from mailed questionnaires to telephone. Each has its own advantages and disadvantages.</page>

</section>
