<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Simple linear regression">
<topText><![CDATA[<p>We have already explored the idea of a relationship between two numerical variables using  <a href=&quot;javascript:nav.gotoshowNamedPage('scatterplot2')&quot;>scatterplots</a>. We have also met the <a href=&quot;javascript:showNamedPage('correlation3')&quot;>correlation coefficient</a>, a numerical summary of the strength of a linear relationship. This section explores bivariate linear relationships further.</p>]]></topText>


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="leastSqrs2" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_leastSqrs2" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_leastSqrs2">A line or curve is useful for predicting the value of Y from a known value of X. A straight line can often be used to predict one variable from another.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="leastSqrs3" summaryDir="en/leastSqrs" summaryFilePrefix="s_leastSqrs3" videoDir="en/leastSqrs" videoFilePrefix="v_leastSqrs3">The difference between the actual value of Y and the value predicted by a line is called a residual. Small residuals are clearly desirable.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="leastSqrs4" summaryDir="en/leastSqrs" summaryFilePrefix="s_leastSqrs4" videoDir="en/leastSqrs" videoFilePrefix="v_leastSqrs4">The sum of squared residuals describes the accuracy of predictions from a line. The method of least squares positions the line to minimise the sum of squared residuals.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnModel_c1" summaryDir="en/regnModel" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnModel_c1" videoDir="en/regnModel" videoFilePrefix="v_regnModel_c1">Some bivariate data sets describe complete populations. Others are 'representative' of an underlying population or process.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnModel_c2" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnModel2" videoDir="en/regnModel" videoFilePrefix="v_regnModel_c2">Bivariate data can be modelled with a response distribution for each possible X. In a normal linear model, we use a normal distribution whose mean is a linear function of X and whose standard deviation is constant.</page>
<page dir="en/regnModel" filePrefix="regnModel4" summaryDir="en/regnModel" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnModel4" videoDir="en/regnModel" videoFilePrefix="v_regnModel4">A normal linar model can be described in terms of 'errors'. In samples from the model, approximately 95% of errors are within 2 standard deviations of zero, so about 95% of the points in a scatterplot are within this distance of the regression line.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="regnModel_c5" summaryDir="en/regnModel" summaryFilePrefix="s_regnModel_c5" videoDir="en/regnModel" videoFilePrefix="v_regnModel_c5">The normal linear model has 3 unknown parameters. For many data sets, these parameters have meaningful interpretations.</page>

<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Pick the explanatory variable and response">For several scenarios, you must identify the explanatory variable and response, then state whether the data are observational or experimental and whether the relationship is causal.</page>
<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a straight line">This exercise shows the equation of a straight line and asks you to sketch it.</page>
<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find the slope and intercept">The exercises on this page do the inverse of the previous exercise — you are shown a straight line and asked to find its equation.</page>
<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Interpret the slope and intercept">In this exercise, you are asked to select one of four statements that correctly describes the slope or intercept of a least squares line in the context of the data.</page>
<page dir="en/leastSqrs" filePrefix="e_leastSqrs5" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Find a residual">This exercise requests the least squares residual for a cross on a scatterplot.</page>

</section>
