<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Distribution of sample mean">


<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean_c1" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean1" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean_c1">A summary value describing a population is called a parameter and the corresponding value in a sample is called a statistic. Sample statistics vary from sample to sample.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean2" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean2" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean2">A sample mean has a distribution that is centred round the population mean, &amp;micro;, but has smaller spread than the population's spread.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean3" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean3" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean3">The spread of the sample mean decreases as sample size increases. A formula is given for the standard deviation of the sample mean in terms of the sample size, n, and population standard deviation, &amp;sigma;.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean4" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean4" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean4">Sample means from normal populations also have normal distributions.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean5" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean5" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean5">The shape of the sample mean's distribution is usually close to normal, even if the population distribution is skew or multimodal. The bigger the sample size, the closer the distribution to normal.</page>
<page dir="en/sumDiff" filePrefix="sumDiff1" nameOverride="Distributions of sums and means" summaryDir="en/sumDiff" summaryFilePrefix="s_sumDiff1" videoDir="en/sumDiff" videoFilePrefix="v_sumDiff1">The mean of a random sample is approximately normal with s.d. equal to &amp;sigma; divided by &amp;radic;n. The sum of a random sample is also approximately normal, but its s.d. is &amp;sigma; times &amp;radic;n.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="randomMean_c6" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean_c6" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean_c6">It is possible to estimate the distribution of a sample mean from a single sample.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="randomMean7" summaryDir="en/randomMean" summaryFilePrefix="s_randomMean7" videoDir="en/randomMean" videoFilePrefix="v_randomMean7">If the sample values are positively correlated, the standard deviation of the mean will be underestimated.</page>

<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="e_randomMean1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Spread of distribution of mean and sum">This exercise shows the distribution of the mean or sum of values from samples of different sizes from a normal population. You must match the distributions with their sample sizes.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="e_randomMean2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Shape of distribution of mean and sum">This exercise examines understanding of the limiting normal distribution of the sample mean and sum as sample size increases, whatever the shape of the population distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="e_randomMean3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Distribution of mean and sum (cont)">In this exercise, pop-up menus are used to specify the centre, spread and skewness of the distribution of a sample mean, sample sum or a single value, given the population distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/randomMean" filePrefix="e_randomMean4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Probabilities relating to means and sums">This exercise asks for the probability that the mean, the sum or a single value from a sample lies within some interval. Templates are provided to help evaluate the parameters of the sampling distribution and the z-scores for the endpoints of the interval.</page>

</section>
