<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Continuous distributions">


<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="continIntro1" summaryDir="bk/masseyBbs" summaryFilePrefix="s_continIntro1">Whereas a discrete variable can only take separate (discrete) values, a continuous numerical variable can take on any value on a continuous scale. For continuous variables, it is meaningful to consider the probability of a value within an interval such as P(0.8&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;&amp;nbsp;X&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;&amp;nbsp;1.2) but  probabilities for specific values such as P(X&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;1.0) are zero.</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity4" nameOverride="Probability density functions" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity4" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity4">If the vertical scale on a histogram is such that the total area under the histogram equals 1 and the class interval becomes very small the histogram takes on the appearance of a smooth curve, called a probability density curve (pdf).</page>
<page dir="en/probDensity" filePrefix="probDensity6" nameOverride="Probability and area under pdf" summaryDir="en/probDensity" summaryFilePrefix="s_probDensity6" videoDir="en/probDensity" videoFilePrefix="v_probDensity6">For a continuous variable, P(a &lt; X &lt; b) is the area under a probability density curve between&amp;nbsp; X = a&amp;nbsp; and&amp;nbsp; X = b. This is how we should visualise the probability, even though in practice we use standard tables or Excel formulae and templates to actually calculate the area (probability).</page>

<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="e_probSim3" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Probabilities and numerical populations">This exercise is simlar to the one on the previous page but relates to a numerical population that is summarised by a histogram. The probability must be estimated roughly 'by eye' from the area under the histogram.</page>
<page dir="en/probSim" filePrefix="e_probSim4" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Probabilities from continuous distributions">In this exercise, probabilities are obtained from the areas under a probability density function.</page>

</section>
