<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">
<section name="Two numerical variables">


<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="scatterplot_c1" summaryDir="en/scatterplot" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterplot1" videoDir="en/scatterplot" videoFilePrefix="v_scatterplot1">Many data sets contain two or more measurements from each individual. Even when the main interest is in one variable, the others can help to understand its distribution.</page>
<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="scatterplot_c2" summaryDir="en/scatterplot" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterplot2" videoDir="en/scatterplot" videoFilePrefix="v_scatterplot_c2">The main display that shows the relationship between two variables is a scatterplot.</page>
<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="scatterplot3" summaryDir="en/scatterplot" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterplot3" videoDir="en/scatterplot" videoFilePrefix="v_scatterplot3">Univariate displays don't show relationships between variables.</page>
<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="scatterplot_c4" summaryDir="en/scatterplot" summaryFilePrefix="s_scatterplot4" videoDir="en/scatterplot" videoFilePrefix="v_scatterplot_c4">A scatterplot of two variables can be enhanced with box plots or histograms on the margins of a scatterplot.</page>
<page dir="en/relationship" filePrefix="relationship_c1" summaryDir="en/relationship" summaryFilePrefix="s_relationship1" videoDir="en/relationship" videoFilePrefix="v_relationship_c1">The main feature of interest in a scatterplot is the strength of the relationship between the two variables.</page>
<page dir="bk/masseyBbs" filePrefix="relationship_c2" summaryDir="en/relationship" summaryFilePrefix="s_relationship2" videoDir="bk/masseyBbs" videoFilePrefix="v_relationship2">An extreme value of one or both of the variables is an outlier. An unusual combination of values is also called an outlier.</page>
<page dir="en/relationship" filePrefix="relationship_c3" summaryDir="en/relationship" summaryFilePrefix="s_relationship3" videoDir="en/relationship" videoFilePrefix="v_relationship3">If the crosses on a scatterplot separate into clusters, different groups of individuals are suggested.</page>
<page dir="en/relationship" filePrefix="relationship_c4" summaryDir="en/relationship" summaryFilePrefix="s_relationship4" videoDir="en/relationship" videoFilePrefix="v_relationship_c4">In small data sets, there may be considerable variability, so patterns should be strongly evident before they are reported.</page>
<page dir="en/relationship" filePrefix="relationship_c5" summaryDir="en/relationship" summaryFilePrefix="s_relationship5" videoDir="en/relationship" videoFilePrefix="v_relationship_c5">One variable can often be classified as an explanatory variable that either causally affects the reponse variable, or is useful for predicting its value.</page>

<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="e_scatterplot1" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Draw a scatterplot">In this exercise, you will complete a scatterplot by dragging the crosses for the last two observations.</page>
<page dir="en/scatterplot" filePrefix="e_scatterplot2" nameOverride="#r#Exercise: #+#Interpret a scatterplot">The exercises in this page expect you to interpret scatterplots in terms of the relationship between the variables, clusters and outliers. In the first exercise, the interpretation is in an application context, whereas in the second the interpretation is in generic terms.</page>

</section>
