<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Sums of squares for other models'>
<topText><![CDATA[
  <p>The pages in this section demonstrate the distributions of the sums of squares 
		in analysis of variance tables for a few more complex models.</p>
	
	<div style="margin-left:50px; margin-right:50px;"><div style="border: 1px solid #999999; font-weight:bold; padding: 4px 12px 4px 12px;">
		<p><span style="color:#FF0000;">Warning:</span> 
						The pages in this section relate to models that were described in 
						earlier chapters. In a previous version of CAST, they were interspersed 
						with earlier practical material so they only provide some 'support' 
						for the earlier anova material.</p>
	</div></div>
	<br>
]]></topText>


<page dir='en/moreAnovaDist' filePrefix='moreAnovaDist1'>This page gives general results about sums of squares, their degrees of freedom and their distributions, for any sequence of models.</page>
<page dir='en/moreAnovaDist' filePrefix='moreAnovaDist2'>In a linear model with 2 numerical explanatory variables, the residual sums of squares has a chi-squared distribution with (n-3) degrees of freedom. The explained regression sum of squares has a chi-squared distribution with 2 degrees of freedom if the response is unrelated to the explanatory variables.</page>
<page dir='en/moreAnovaDist' filePrefix='moreAnovaDist3'>In a quadratic model, the quadratic sum of squares has a chi-squared distribution if the true model is linear, but its distribution has a larger mean if there is curvature.</page>
<page dir='en/moreAnovaDist' filePrefix='moreAnovaDist4'>The between-group and within-group sums of squares have chi-squared distributions and the anova F ratio has an F distribution if both group means are equal. The p-value for the anova test is the tail area of this distribution.</page>
<page dir='en/moreAnovaDist' filePrefix='moreAnovaDist5'>The sums of squares again have chi-squared distributions but with different degrees of freedom.</page>

</section>
