<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Several explanatory variables'>


<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova1'>The marginal sums of squares in a general linear model describe the effect on the residual sum of squares of deleting single variables from the full model. </page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova2'>The variable with smallest marginal sum of squares is least important and its p-value indicates whether it can be dropped from the model. The marginal sums of squares can be recalculated and further variables dropped in an iterative procedure.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova3'>When the explanatory variables are uncorrelated, parameter estimates and marginal sums of squares are unaffected by removing other variables. Variance inflation factors indicate the degree of multicollinearity.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova4'>Sequential sums of squares describe changes to the residual sum of squares when the explanatory variables are added sequentially. The sums of squares depend on the order of adding the variables.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova5'>The sequential sums of squares are also the sum of squared differences between the fitted values of consecutive models. In some applications, these differences can be shown graphically to illustrate the sequential sum of squares.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova6'>The sequential sums of squares depend on the order of adding the variables except with the explanatory variables are uncorrelated.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova7'>Individual explanatory variables can be grouped together by adding their sums of squares and degrees of freedom.</page>
<page dir='en/glmAnova' filePrefix='glmAnova8'>The sum of squares table can be extended with mean sums of squares and F ratios. P-values can be found for the F ratios to indicate whether each variable can be dropped from the model, but these should only be interpreted when subsequent p-values are not significant.</page>

</section>
