<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Correlation'>
<topText><![CDATA[
	<p>This section describes a numerical summary of the strength of the relationship between two variables, X and Y.</p>
]]></topText>


<page dir='en/relationship' filePrefix='relationship1'>The main feature of interest in a scatterplot is the strength of the relationship between the two variables.</page>

<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation1'>A numerical description of the strength of a relationship should not be affected by rescaling the variables.</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation2'>Standardising a variable gives z-scores that do not depend on the units of the original variable. (The correlation coefficient will be defined in terms of z-scores for X and Y.)</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation3'>The correlation coefficient summarises the strength of the relationship between X and Y. It is +1 when the scatterplot crosses are on a straight line with positive slope, -1 when on a line with negative slope, and zero when X and Y are unrelated.</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation4'>You should be able to estimate the value of r from looking at a scatterplot and imagine a scatter of crosses corresponding to any value of r.</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation5'>The correlation coefficient is only a good measure of the strength of a relationship if the points in a scatterplot are scattered round a straight line, not a curve.</page>
<page dir='en/correlation' filePrefix='correlation6'>The correlation coefficient cannot identify curvature, outliers or clusters and can be misleading if these features are present. A scatterplot must always be examined too.</page>

<page dir='en/relationship' filePrefix='relationship2'>An extreme value of one or both of the variables is an outlier. An unusual combination of values is also called an outlier.</page>
<page dir='en/relationship' filePrefix='relationship3'>If the crosses on a scatterplot separate into clusters, different groups of individuals are suggested.</page>
<page dir='en/relationship' filePrefix='relationship4'>In small data sets, there may be considerable variability, so patterns should be strongly evident before they are reported.</page>

</section>
