<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Numerical and categorical explanatory variables' shortName='Numerical &amp;amp; categorical variables'>


<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel1'>A simple linear model for Y against X can be augmented with a 0/1 indicator variable distinguishing the groups. The model is a GLM and can be represented by two parallel lines on the scatterplot of Y vs X.</page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel2'>A t-test for whether the coefficient of the indicator variable is zero tests whether the groups are the same.</page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel3'>If there are g groups, (g-1) indicator variables can be added to the simple linear model. This corresponds to g parallel lines for the groups on the scatterplot of Y vs X.</page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel4'>Analysis of variance provides a single test for differences between the groups. If X is not orthogonal to the groups, there are two different anova tables corresponding to the two orders of adding X and the indicator variables.</page>
<page dir='en/structures' filePrefix='structures3'>Observations that are split into groups can be equivalently considered as a single data set with a categorical variable defining group membership.</page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel6'>Data with two categorical explanatory variables often arise from designed experiments. Two sets of indicator variables can be used to model the effects of the two variables in a GLM.</page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel7'>The effects of the categorical explanatory variables can be tested with analysis of variance. The categorical explanatory variables are usually orthogonal in designed experiments and a single anova table can test both variables. </page>
<page dir='en/mixedModel' filePrefix='mixedModel8'>The models in this section can be extended with terms for any mixture of numerical and categorical explanatory variables. If one or more categorical explanatory variables has 3+ levels, F-tests based on Type 3 sums of squares should be used to test significance instead of t-tests for individual parameters.</page>

</section>
