<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../../../structure/sectionXmlDefn.dtd">

<section name='Nonlinear relationships'>


<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo1'>A general linear model is linear in its parameters, but not necessarily in the explanatory variables. Models with transformed variables and with quadratic terms are all general linear models.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo2' note='(optional)'>A model with a linear term and a quadratic term in x is still linear in the parameters and is a general linear model.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo3'>Polynomial models have terms involving various powers of x and are flexible ways to model curvature. As the order of the polynomial increases, the curve can become less smooth. Polynomials are usually poor for extrapolation.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo4'>For detecting curvature when there is more than one explanatory variable, it is better to plot residuals rather than the raw data.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo5'>If a plot of residuals against X shows curvature, a partial residual plot can give an indication of which nonlinear function of X to use in the model.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo6'>If the response in related linearly to Z but nonlinearly to X, a quadratic term in X can be added to the model to explain the curvature. The resulting model corresponds to a curved surface in a 3-dimensional scatterplot.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo7'>Quadratic terms in both X and Z can be added, resulting in a surface that is curved in both X and Z directions.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo8'>The residuals from a quadratic model can be represented as vertical lines from data points to the quadratic surface. If squares are drawn for each residual, least squares means minimising the total area of these squares.</page>
<page dir='en/nonlinTwo' filePrefix='nonlinTwo9'>Curvature can be assessed with t-test about whether the two quadratic parameters are non-zero.</page>

</section>
